<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gallant hermaphrodite an amorous novel / translated from the French of the sieur de Chavigny.</title>
            <title>Galante hermaphrodite. English</title>
            <author>Chavigny de La Bretonnière, François de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3757A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9231</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12147155</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12147155</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32774)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 87:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gallant hermaphrodite an amorous novel / translated from the French of the sieur de Chavigny.</title>
                  <title>Galante hermaphrodite. English</title>
                  <author>Chavigny de La Bretonnière, François de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 123 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F.C. for N.C. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Galante hermaphrodite.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed June 7, 1687. R.P."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54982:1"/>
            <p>The Gallant Hermaphrodite. An Amorous NOVEL.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated from the <hi>French,</hi> OF The <hi>Sieur de Chavigny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licenſed,</p>
                        <closer>
                           <date>
                              <hi>June</hi> 7. 1687.</date>
                           <signed>R. P.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>F. C.</hi> for <hi>N. C.</hi> in <hi>Oxon.</hi> MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:54982:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54982:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>WEre it not to put an end to the Bookſellers Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, I ſhould not trouble you with a Preface; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given him the Novel, I am not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige him by halves. Though I am alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at a loſs what to ſay, when I call to mind the Reflection of a witty Author,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In vain the Preface doth for Favour plead,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where the damn'd Book diſpleaſes all that read.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> For whatſoever this Piece of the <hi>Sieur de Chavigny</hi> be in the Original, I am ſure it has ſuffer'd much in my hands. Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations are for the moſt part like a Suit of <hi>Arras,</hi> turn'd the wrong ſide outwards; and therefore you muſt expect to find This full of Knots and Thrums, ſince 'tis my firſt <hi>Coup d'Eſſay</hi> (as Sir <hi>Fopling</hi> ſays) in this kind. Such as it is, I make a free Preſent of it to the lovely Sex, in
<pb facs="tcp:54982:3"/>hopes of their Patronage; eſpecially to that part of it who have a Kindneſs for what is originally French. As to thoſe Ladies who delight in the ſight of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephants, Hairy Maids, Turks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I hope our <hi>Gallant Hermaphrodite</hi> will be kindly entertain'd by them, ſince they may, without ſcandal, even in their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coves, freely view and converſe with this—what ſhall we call it?
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sir, or Madam, chuſe you whether;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nature twiſts them both together.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q> All the further Favour I deſire, Ladies, is, that you would put bounds to your Curioſity, and not endeavour to pull off my diſguiſe; but content your ſelves with laughing at my Pains, without laughing at my Face. But if any of you will be ſo malicious to lay this Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of a Tranſlation at my door, I am reſolv'd, in revenge, impudently to maintain 'tis a Baſtard of your own, and falſly put upon me to Father.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54982:3"/>
            <head>The Gallant Hermaphrodite.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ARagon, Portugal,</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile,</hi> acknowledged each of them a Soveraign; this laſt Court, where Magnificence reign'd, attracted from the Borders of the <hi>Weſt</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> ſo great a concourſe of young Princes, that it had been very hard, ſhould it not have ſerv'd for a Theatre to ſome extraordinary Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture. Some publick Sports inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted for the Exerciſe of ſuch Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous young Perſons, and in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of which, thoſe of both Sexes had chang'd their Names to thoſe of ſome <hi>Deity</hi> in Poetry, gave birth to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54982:4"/>the firſt Flames of a young Prince of the Royal Family of <hi>Braganza,</hi> nam'd <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who repreſented <hi>Mercury;</hi> and to the mutual inclinations of the Dutcheſs <hi>Anna Iphigenia,</hi> the High Admiral's Daughter, who perſonated <hi>Flora.</hi> That nimble <hi>God</hi> having bore away the honour of the Courſe, this <hi>Goddeſs</hi> preſented him with a Chaplet of Flowers (as an Emblem of her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity) with ſo good a grace, that he could not forbear from requiting her agreeable ways of procedure, by the return of his Heart. He ſtay'd not for the day following the Feaſt, to ſhew her how ſenſible he was of the Favour which he had receiv'd from her, more valuing the having receiv'd the Garland from ſo fair a Perſon's hands, than the having gain'd the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory. He declared to her openly before all the Court, that ſhe tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umpht over the Conquerour, and laid at her feet the Prize with which his Valour and Addreſs had been recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penc'd.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54982:4"/>'Twas from this moment, that theſe two tender Hearts were u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited, that they began to ſigh the one for the other, and that they form'd an inviolable Union. If <hi>Mercury</hi> grew paſſionately in love with <hi>Flora, Flora</hi> was in love with <hi>Mercury;</hi> ſo that they courted every occaſion to ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize their love to each other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia</hi> had all the Charms that could render a Princeſs of ſixteen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely lovely, and the young Prince who was about two and twenty, was endow'd with all the Qualities that accompliſh a Grandee. The love that <hi>Alphonſus</hi> conceiv'd for this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Beauty, was from its birth, of the character of that which is term'd vehement. It made a noiſe at Court, inſomuch that the <hi>Queen,</hi> whoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue had drawn this young <hi>Princeſs</hi> from another Court, fearing leſt ſo mutual and ſtrong a Paſſion might produce ſomething prejudicial to the Ladies Honour, took her into the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54982:5"/>number of her Favourites, that ſhe might keep her always by her, and committed her to the care of an old <hi>Governeſs,</hi> whoſe Eyes it was very difficult for her to deceive. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, as Love is exaſperated by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, the more Obſtacles <hi>Alphonſus</hi> found to ſurmount, the more his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion increaſed. There was no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity offered it ſelf of entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing privately the <hi>Dutcheſs Iphigenia,</hi> which he let ſlip. He very rarely was out of her preſence, inſomuch that he gave occaſion to ſome other young Lords to divert themſelves, at his coſt, ſo far, that one of the wittieſt amongſt them compos'd this Raillery upon his Aſſiduities.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of his Devoir himſelf t'acquit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Alphonſus <hi>every-where does watch,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(With his beſt Care and utmoſt Wit)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Glance from the bright Fair to catch;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:54982:5"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But hardly doth he her eſpie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When at the preſence of her Charms,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Struck with the Luſtre of her Eye,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He yields his Heart up to her Arms.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>All the Precautions of her who watcht our fair ones Conduct, could not deprive <hi>Alphonſus</hi> of the pleaſure of entertaining her often in private. The more the <hi>Queen,</hi> who lookt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Alliance as impoſſible (for very different reaſons than thoſe which hindred it indeed) oppos'd their deſires, the more their Love became impatient, and contriv'd means to ſurprize the vigilance of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Iphigenia</hi> bethought her ſelf to make a Viſit to the <hi>Princeſs Chriſtina, Alphonſus</hi>'s Siſter, with whom ſhe was very familiar; but as he was at variance with her, he could hardly reſolve to ſacrifice the reſentment of many ſtinging Reproaches which ſhe had made him, to ſome ſweet mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that might be recovered elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54982:6"/>This Conſideration induc'd our Illuſtrious Fair One (to avoid diſobliging the <hi>Queen,</hi> and opening a hundred young Ladies mouths who would railly her Paſſion) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to Prince <hi>Alphonſus</hi> a Truce, to whom ſhe ſuggeſted the common Correſpondence by Letters. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, as all things are diſcovered at long run, and as it is difficult to find truſty <hi>Confidents</hi> at Court, our Illuſtrious Lovers ſufficiently thought upon the intercepting of their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to agree together of a way to conceal their intelligence from the curioſity of People that are apt to laugh. They contriv'd then to reject the firſt word of every Line as uſeleſs to the ſence, and to ſearch after the Coherency of the Diſcourſe, in skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping over one word to the next, and ſo going backwards again in the ſame manner, being at the end, even to the beginning. This is a Copy of the Letter which the Amorous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54982:6"/>
               <hi>Prince</hi> made, according to this my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Irregular Order of Prince <hi>Alphonſus</hi> his Letter.</head>
                  <p>THE) <hi>the Anſwer Deſtiny an of with great me men honour</hi> curious) <hi>is Lovers more of cruel faithful</hi> will) <hi>than moſt the the Deſtiny faith of his thoſe of of day a this meaner you</hi> be) <hi>fortune makes if that we engage</hi>-enrag'd) <hi>ment were the of</hi> Flora <hi>that charming Rank approve we reſolution</hi> not) <hi>ſhould generous be a freer of what</hi> to) <hi>capable always is Slaves age in our our that independency ſee when them</hi> enter) <hi>ſhall make I ſhall be we able love</hi> into) <hi>to in ſay paſſionately that am I I adore that you ſenſible extreamly but</hi> our) <hi>becauſe are that you you if are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion abſolutely our lovely to what</hi> Secrets) <hi>bring ſo can ever Interest hindrance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:54982:7"/>
            <p>This innocent Artifice ſucceeded ill to our Lovers. How faithful ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Maid of the Dutcheſs <hi>Iphigenia</hi> ſeem'd to <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> and whatſoever proteſtations ſhe made him to put his Letter faithfully into her Miſtreſs's hands; the Governeſs ſo abſolutely diſpoſed of all her Domeſticks, frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by her threats, that ſhe intercepted the Letter, whereof notwithſtanding ſhe could not underſtand the ſence. She made a Copy of it to be taken, which ſhe went to communicate to the <hi>Queen,</hi> and ordered that the Original ſhould be delivered in ſecret to the young Dutcheſs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Queen</hi> truſted this myſterious Note with her <hi>Secretary,</hi> who after an hours meditation, decypher'd it with much eaſe, and read it thus.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:54982:7"/>
                  <head>Prince <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s Letter, in its natural Order.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THE Deſtiny of great men is more cruel than the Deſtiny of thoſe of a meaner Fortune. If we were of that Bank, we ſhould be freer. What! al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Slaves in our Independency? when ſhall I be able to ſay, that I adore you extreamly, becauſe that you are abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lovely? Whatſoever hindrance Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt can bring to our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, if you are but ſenſible that I am paſſionately in love, we ſhall make them ſee that our Age is capable of a generous Reſolution. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, charming</hi> Flora, <hi>the Engagement that makes you of his Faith, the most faithful of Lovers. Honour me with an Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The <hi>Queen,</hi> who was a very wiſe Princeſs, judg'd by this Letter, of the great Familiarity of theſe tender Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54982:8"/>and the conſequences that it might produce. Her Prudence ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted nothing elſe to her, only to order the <hi>Governeſs</hi> to interrupt this Amorous Commerce, as much as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency would allow, and to forbid her taking notice of any thing to the young <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> concerning the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting of her Letter. Whilſt <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia</hi> was buſied in anſwering the <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> that ſhe had receiv'd, the <hi>Governeſs</hi> entred her Chamber. Her unexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed arrival made her put her Papers together with the greateſt haſte ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, and appear'd ſome time di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed. After ſome ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, the <hi>Governeſs</hi> having pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely brought in Prince <hi>Alphonſus</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Diſcourſe, the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> ſeem'd very indifferent on that Chapter, and let nothing appear that might betray her Love. That cunning Woman ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving by the diſorder that appear'd in <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s looks, that ſhe had been ſurpriz'd, and that ſhe ſhould be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſom
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54982:8"/>if ſhe kept her company long, retir'd to leave her at liberty to betake her ſelf to her former Employment.</p>
            <p>This Fair One found her ſelf per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex'd, to make an Anſwer conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Note; ſhe ſpar'd her pains, in hopes that one of <hi>Alphonſus</hi> his Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Maids would do her the Courteſie to convey a Letter writ the common way, to the Party concern'd. In ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, this complaiſant Maid, whoſe name was <hi>Cornelia,</hi> found opportunity to ſatisfie her, and to deliver the young Prince her Letter, who immediately gave her marks of his Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This is the ſubſtance of the Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Dutcheſs <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF you love me as ſincerely as you would perſwade me, ſpeak well of Deſtiny, that makes you born a Prince. Perſons of our Rank are born free, or are at moſt,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54982:9"/>Slaves but for a very little time. The viciſſitude of Seaſons will change the face of Affairs. Let us conſider for ſome time. Be you faithful to Love, and he will ſufficiently eſpouſe your Intereſt. I love as much as you love, becauſe I have not a lower Soul, and that I love to the utmoſt extent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Prince,</salute> Adieu</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>A Letter written in terms ſo plain and paſſionate, ſtrongly flattred <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi>'s amorous inclination, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that, remain'd ſome time in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>Although <hi>Iphigenia</hi> ſuſpected not the fidelity of her perfidious Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, ſhe perceiv'd nevertheleſs, by the Aſſiduities that the Queen required from her, and the frequent Viſits of her Governeſs, that they had a ſpight againſt her liberty. One day that ſhe met <hi>Alphonſus</hi> near enough at a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, whoſe motions the Queen ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, and ſtudied all his looks, ſhe took ſo well her time, that ſhe told
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54982:9"/>him, without being underſtood by any one whatſoever; Alphonſus, <hi>we ſhall not be able to ſee one another again with liberty, but at your Siſters; reconcile your ſelf to her, and let none but the Maid that has given you my Anſwer, know of your Reconciliation. I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare her Mind, and I will manage your Honour and Intereſt as my own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was nothing but Love that could perſwade <hi>Alphonſus</hi> to that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying advance, to ſee again a Siſter that had a thouſand times provok'd his Nature. It was the greateſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to him in the World, to reſolve on it; and without the meeting with one of his Siſters Maids, which was the Confident of the Dutcheſs <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> I queſtion if his Love had been able to have carried it above his Reſentment. He engag'd this Maid, equally witty and diſcreet, to encline his Siſter afar off, to court his Friendſhip, in repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to her, that when Heaven could not but have in horrour their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54982:10"/>ſeparation, it was ſhameful to ſee Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of their Quality and near Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, live in a miſunderſtanding, that rendred them the ſport of the Court. He promis'd to this Mediatrix to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge her Services, and that if Heaven made him obtain the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> ſhe might flatter her ſelf with the hope of a conſiderable Fortune. Now for fear that their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview ſhould become ſuſpected, he ſhew'd her the Wife of a Steward of the Kings Houſhold, to whom ſhe might give an account of her Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelia</hi> inſtructed in the deſigns of <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> run to communicate them to the Illuſtrious Miſtriſs of this <hi>Prince,</hi> who ſuggeſted to her the manner whereby ſhe ſhould inſinuate her ſelf into the mind of the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> ſhe counſelled her to move this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame Evening, that ſhe would come to ſee this Princeſs on purpoſe, whereby ſhe would ſtrongly try her
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54982:10"/>Inclination, in reſpect of <hi>Alphonſus</hi> her Brother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelia</hi> was playing the fool with the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who hid none of her thoughts from her, when ſhe told her that ſhe had had a Dream during which, ſhe found her ſelf the moſt happy Maid in the World. There was a likelihood that the ſight of ſome agreeable Object had enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained her, and that there paſſed, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this Dream, ſomething too wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton to be related, ſince that ſhe made a myſtery of it to this Confident, to whom ſhe would never reveal it, what entreaty ſoever ſhe made. They conteſted yet agreeably together with that privacy that ſhe permitted to <hi>Cornelia,</hi> when one came to adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina</hi> of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival of <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> whoſe Coach was in the Court. She bid her tell her that ſhe thought her ſelf much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by her Viſit, and that ſhe was ready to receive her.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:54982:11"/>
            <p>She mounted the Stair-caſe with her ordinary freedom, when ſhe heard in an adjacent Parlour many Maids laughing at the Tales, which an old Woman told them, who by looking in their hands told them their good Fortune. As ſhe was familiar and beloved by all the Houſe, ſhe ſtopt there, and inform'd her ſelf of the cauſe of ſo extraordinary a Gaiety: She underſtood it, and pray'd them not to diſmiſs this Fortune-teller, till that ſhe had ſpoke of her in the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Princeſs.</p>
            <p>The Prince <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who knew the free humour of his Siſter, had ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born'd this Woman, who was famous for her knowledge in <hi>Chiromancy,</hi> even to the foretelling of things to come. He had inſtructed her in part of his Siſters Life, and ordered her above all things, to predict to her, that diſmal Conſequences would ſpring from the miſunderſtanding that was between her Brother and her.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54982:11"/>This Prince knew well, that <hi>Cornelia</hi> would ſerve his Intereſts, and would yet add as much as was poſſible for her, to the impreſſion of Predictions; and 'twas this that induc'd him to advertiſe her to ask for her at the Palace, in caſe that the <hi>Swiſs</hi> ſhould deny her En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance. This old Woman was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to act her part to the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the whole houſe, when <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia,</hi> that was not pre-acquainted with his deſign, heard her.</p>
            <p>After the ordinary Complements paſs'd between theſe two Princeſſes, their diſcourſe, after having been ſome time ſerious, turning to free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Iphigenia</hi> intreated the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina</hi> to be willing to permit the old Woman to come up, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt would afford them diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement. The Princeſs, who was not leſs curious than <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> agreed preſently to the Propoſition: The old Woman was brought into the Chamber, and there aroſe an agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54982:12"/>Conteſt between the two Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, which ſhould preſent their Hand firſt. They were curious to hear the Recital of each others Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, and each defended her ſelf from having the firſt Experiment made on her. <hi>Cornelia,</hi> who was more an Enemy to Gallantry than the Princeſſes, and who had as well as they, her ſecret Intrigues, fearing to be forc'd firſt to paſs the Pikes, pretended ſome occaſion to go out; and 'twas this pretence that made them caſt their Eyes on her, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her to preſent her Hand. She obey'd and this cunning old Woman told her preſently a thouſand obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging things, for fear of frighting the Princeſſes: But as ſhe receiv'd Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands from them not to ſpare her, ſhe told this Maid, amongſt other things, that ſhe was belov'd by three ſeveral Perſons; by two Cavaliers, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon whom ſhe nam'd <hi>Baptem,</hi> and whoſe Birth equall'd not his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54982:12"/>Wealth. She added, that ſhe had an inclination for the uglieſt of the three, which nevertheleſs ſeem'd to her to have ſomething amiable; which made the Princeſs ſay, that without doubt 'twas Monſieur ſuch a one; which <hi>Cornelia</hi> ſo little agreed to, that ſhe forgot even what ſhe was, through the backwardneſs ſhe ſhew'd at the earneſt demand that was made her, to confeſs if it was true. <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who would not vex this Maid, of whoſe interceſſion ſhe might ſtand in need, pretended not to obſerve her ill humour, and diverted the buſineſs ſo handſomly, that ſhe ory'd out laughing, and addreſſing her ſelf to the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina, Madam, your Turn's next.</hi> This Princeſs waver'd ſo very much, and had ſo great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to preſent this pretended Mirrour of her Soul, that the particular incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> ſeconded by the impreſſion of Deſtiny, made her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to give her Hand, on condition
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54982:13"/>that the Princeſs ſhould follow her Example. This Agreement made between them, the old Woman en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larg'd upon a hundred paſs'd Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that ſurpriz'd <hi>Iphigenia</hi> ſo very much, that ſhe believ'd her truly a Sorcereſs. She was not for all that, ſo ſcrupulous as to fear venturing her Conſcience, and therefore ſhe let her make an end of ſaying all that her evil Genius ſuggeſted to her. After having heard a thouſand probable things, ſhe had the ſmarting ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to hear the moſt croſs Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtications imaginable: <hi>You ſhall be lov'd,</hi> ſays ſhe, <hi>and you ſhall love. You ſhall ſigh only for Objects worthy of you. You ſhall be perfidious and faithful<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> You ſhall furniſh Occaſion for a Tragedy. You ſhall obtain the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of your Vows. You ſhall be a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Rival, and you ſhall lead a happy Life, full of Proſperity and Tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with the Perſon that thinks leaſt to obtain you.</hi> So many obſcure and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54982:13"/>confus'd Predictions paſs'd in the mind of <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> for meer Fancies and Prognoſtications in the Air. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, the ſequel of this Princeſs's Adventures juſtified their truth. But let us paſs over to what was made known in examining the Lines of the Princeſs's hand, the Siſter of <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> for whoſe Inſtruction our old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was ſent thither.</p>
            <p>The great ſeriouſneſs which this Princeſs affected, who had heard too much upon <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s account, not to fear hearing ſome diſagreeable Truths, diſordred preſently the old Woman, who endeavour'd to utter none but Events whoſe Remembrance ſhould extreamly pleaſe, till <hi>Iphige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> having told her, that ſhe would not be ſatisfied that the Princeſs ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Reſerve and Flattery, ſo that ſhe need not act againſt her knowledge, ſhe ventured to ſpeak more freely. <hi>All your Wiſhes,</hi> purſued ſhe, <hi>are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled; you ſhall experience a favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54982:14"/>Deſtiny, and altogether reſembling that of Madam,</hi> ſaid ſhe, ſhewing her the Princeſs <hi>Iphigenia. One thing, nevertheleſs, is wanting to you, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam; but unleſs you expreſly command me to reveal it to you, I ſhall paſs it over in ſilence.</hi> One may well ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that in ſtopping thus, ſhe ſtirr'd up the curioſity of the one and the other. The <hi>Princeſs</hi> not being able handſomly to defend her ſelf from entreating her to tell her freely her Thoughts, the old Woman added, with aſſurance, That it was not very commendable for her to live in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding with one of her neareſt Relations: That the delay of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation might be prejudicial to her; and that if ſhe would do Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to her ſelf, ſhe ought to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that this Relation was not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to blame; and that in fine, it was her Intereſt to make ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and to court his Friendſhip. This confident Declaration, which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54982:14"/>very much pleas'd <hi>Iphigenia</hi> and the Maid, ſurpriz'd the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> who would know no more, and call'd the old Woman Dotard. She was then diſmiſt. After ſome Reflections that our Ladies made together upon what had been foretold them, <hi>Iphigenia</hi> took her time to expreſs that ſhe was altogether aſtoniſh'd, that this old Woman had been able to reveal the difference of the <hi>Princeſs</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> her Brother. The Princeſs, whom ſuch plain Declarations aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd not leſs than the others, could not keep from crying out, <hi>Fables! Fables! Conjectures found upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing! Iphigenia,</hi> who interrupted her, told her, that in truth ſhe was not of opinion that one ought to be ſuperſtitious to that point, to give credit to all things uttered, nor to fear very much the application and effect of Predictions: But that neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, it was prudence to uſe precaution againſt Events the leaſt dangerous;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54982:15"/>that as for the reſt, for what regarded the falling out between her and the Prince <hi>Alphonſus</hi> her Brother, it would always be a thing to be commended in her to diſſipate it, or to contribute at leaſt in what depended upon her, that the fire of their diſſention might be extinguiſh'd as ſoon as poſſible. Although this kind of Leſſon did not extreamly pleaſe the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> ſhe receiv'd it, without confuſion, from her Friend, from which it came, becauſe ſhe believ'd her not to ſpeak for Intereſt. <hi>Iphigenia</hi> ſeeing her not far from an Accommodation, ſaid to her, <hi>Madam, without having regard to the Chimerical Threats of a Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Old Woman, but purely through a Principle of a Chriſtian Charity, it is neceſſary that your Generoſity now triumph over your Reſentment, and that you ſuffer the Lord</hi> Alphonſus <hi>to repair hither this Evening. I have authority enough over him; and I know beſides, that he eſteems and loves
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54982:15"/>you too tenderly, not to be willing to make the firſt ſtep. I grant you but two hours to reſolve on it. He ſhall himſelf do all that I ſhall preſcribe him by a Note under my Hand, which</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia <hi>ſhall give him. I am perſwaded,</hi> interrupted ſhe the Princeſs, <hi>that my Brother adores you, that he has conceiv'd ſo high an Idaea of your Merit, that he cannot reſiſt obeying you; that you rule all his Motions, not to ſay, that you are the Soveraign of his Heart. I, Madam,</hi> reply'd <hi>Iphigenia. I think not advantageouſly enough of my Charms, to pretend to that glory. The Prince</hi> Alphonſus <hi>is altogether judicious, and 'tis that makes me hope that he will give ear to Reaſon, and not keep him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from following it.</hi> The <hi>Princeſs</hi> reliſh'd the Propoſal of <hi>Iphigenia.</hi> It was agreed on, that <hi>Cornelia</hi> ſhould follow her, and that ſhe ſhould receive from her a Note for the Lord <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:54982:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> at her return, took her Pen in hand, and writ, with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diligence, this Word of Advice to Prince <hi>Alphonſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Billet of <hi>IPHIGENIA,</hi> TO Prince <hi>ALPHONS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF your Love ought to be without partition, you ought not,</hi> Prince, <hi>to be entire in any thing. The Houſe of the Princeſs</hi> Chriſtina, <hi>will be most favourable to your Vows. I deſire this Evening to diſcourſe with you there; fail not at the Aſſignation. You ought to make the firſt Advances in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of your Reconciliation, becauſe you ought to ſeem the moſt generous: go not from my word in any thing. If it is in any manner to humble your ſelf, know that Submiſſions of this nature are Heroick Treaties; that the</hi> Stoicks
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54982:16"/>
                     <hi>will give you the Title of a Valiant Spirit, and the</hi> Sages <hi>that of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. A true Lover cannot do an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Action. If he commits any, they paſs for Virtues, when he relates them to the Object for which he ſighs. The reſt anon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Prince,</salute> Adieu.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Cornelia</hi> charg'd with this Billet, carry'd it to the Lord <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who knew ſo well to counterfeit the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cital ſhe made him concerning the Predictions of the old Woman, that ſhe could never ſuſpect that ſhe had been his Emiſſary. He promis'd to repair to the Houſe after the Play, and really did ſo about Eight a Clock at Night. <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented him there, and who had given the laſt motion to the Reſolution of the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> was no ſooner inform'd of his coming up Stairs, but ſhe went to meet him, and call'd to him at the door, <hi>My Lord</hi> Alphonſus, <hi>enter without Retinue, and leave below
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54982:17"/>your Fierceneſs and Reſentment.</hi> She had hardly finiſh'd theſe words, when the young Prince, who carried Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity drawn on his Face, and Love in his Eyes, appear'd. She inform'd the <hi>Princeſs</hi> of his approach, who roſe from her Chair of State, and went to meet him as far as the Door. Some tender Embraces, without many words, put an end to their Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. After that moment, there appear'd no more Coldneſs between them; and <hi>Alphonſus</hi> entertain'd his Siſter with, as much familiarity, as if they had never been at difference. After ſome moments ſpent in a free Converſation, to which <hi>Iphigenia</hi> had almoſt all the while contributed, the <hi>Princeſs</hi> asked the Lord <hi>Alphonſus.</hi> If he was yet Maſter of his Heart; to which the <hi>Prince</hi> anſwer'd, That he had ſacrificed it to the Graces of the Charming <hi>Iphigenia:</hi> and that lovely <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> anſwer'd him ſo tenderly, that ſhe had given him her own in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54982:17"/>requital. That the Princeſs ſung up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the account of this exchange of Hearts, very much to the purpoſe, this Stanza of a Song made upon a like Subject.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Burn, happy Lovers, burn in Love;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>See that your Flames immortal prove.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be you but conſtant, faithful, kind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And you'll the ſweeteſt moments find</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lovers ere taſted; let each Heart</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In mutual Love ſtill bear a part:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Love your Souls will ſo confound,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In kind Embraces they'll be drown'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>The good humour of the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtiana,</hi> excited Freedom in our two Illuſtrious Lovers, who began to tell one another tender things, and to make Proteſtations of Fidelity to each other. The <hi>Princeſs,</hi> who had not in ſo young years a Judgment ripe enough to diſcern the Intereſts of States compromis'd in the Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Princes, flatter'd at that time
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:54982:18"/>their Paſſion; and counſelled them not to diſpute ſo long time with each other, but to ſearch out the beſt means to give each other Aſſurances of their Love.</p>
            <p>This Advice, although ill weigh'd, agreed extreamly to the Sentiments of <hi>Alphonſus.</hi> It infinitely pleas'd the Dutcheſs <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who conjur'd the <hi>Princeſs</hi> to agree, that ſhe might come every day to her Houſe to paſs ſome moments with the Prince <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus,</hi> until that Heaven had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed their Marriage. The <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> very well perceiv'd by this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that her Brother had not again courted her Amity, but for having the liberty of her Houſe, where <hi>Iphigenia</hi> might come alone, without giving Umbrage to her Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs, who would not imagine that the Lord <hi>Alphonſus</hi> would ſo eaſily hearken to a Reconciliation. In ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſhe did it with ſo little noiſe, that during more than a month our Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54982:18"/>Lovers had the convenience to entertain one another privately, and to open their Hearts to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs, as it was difficult that ſuch a Commerce ſhould remain ſecret at Court, where great Perſons are watch'd by as many Eyes as <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> had, and have as many Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of their Life, as they have Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks; <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s Governeſs, who never could meet her at home in the Evening, having inform'd her ſelf of the Rendezvouz of our Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, went to give an Account to the <hi>Queen,</hi> of their ſecret practices; who obtain'd from the King, that <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> ſhould not ſee <hi>Iphigenia</hi> any more.</p>
            <p>Our Illuſtrious Lovers began but to taſte the preliminary Sweets of Love, when the Malice of a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Fate came to traverſe their ſpringing Pleaſure. The <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> to whom the <hi>Queen</hi> on her ſide had
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54982:19"/>read very diſagreeable Lectures, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented no more almoſt the Houſe of the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> for fear to meet her dear <hi>Alphonſus</hi> there, who loſt alſo the habit of coming to the Houſe, not to ſeem a Rebel to the <hi>King</hi>'s Orders. They endeavour'd, the one and the other, to ward ſo rude a Blow, by the moſt flattering conſiderations that Hope could produce. <hi>Iphige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> did her ſelf ſo much violence to hinder her Grief from breaking out, that ſhe fell into a drooping that reduc'd her to extreamity; ſhe kept her Bed fifteen days, during which time, it was not permitted Prince <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> to come to comfort her with his preſence. Her oppreſſion in the mean time became ſo prodigious, that in her Raving Fits, with which ſhe was agitated, and which differ'd nothing from Madneſs, ſhe would not ſpeak but of her dear <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> to whom <hi>Cornelia</hi> made a tender Report of the ſtate of her Health. She was
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54982:19"/>but ſome days recovered, and went not yet out of her Chamber, when <hi>Alphonſus</hi> who alter'd viſibly, and was fallen into a profound Melancholy, writ this <hi>Billet-doux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>MY Heart is without motion, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Princeſs, and reſents all the Alterations of yours. Are we then ſo criminal, that they condemn us to death? The Melancholy which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours me, gives me it. I expire every time that I hear of your pitiful Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and as I inform my ſelf of it each moment, I preſume to tell you, that I no longer live. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>phold your ſelf, adorable</hi> Iphigenia, <hi>and let the thoughts of what's to come, elevate you above the preſent Perſecutions. In the deplora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Eſtate Inhumanity has reduc'd me to, I can yet diſpute it even to Death, if I hear that in that little Life is left you, you yet turn your Thoughts towards the faithful</hi> Alphonſus.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:54982:20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia</hi> ſteeped this tender Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in her Tears. She was very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous in the extreamity wherein ſhe was to anſwer it: But beſides, that her weakneſs would not ſuffer her to hold a Pen, her Bed was always ſo beſieged with Ladies that made her troubleſom Viſits, that ſhe could not find the conveniency of diſcourſing one moment with <hi>Cornelia,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of her and her Lover.</p>
            <p>This Letter reviv'd her Love. She became ſo impatient to ſee her dear <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> that ſo long an abſence threw her into a Melancholy that caus'd her Relapſe. Her Diſtemper increaſed, and her Raving Fits recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menc'd. Her Mind was wholly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up with the Anſwer that ſhe would make to her Lovers <hi>Billet,</hi> which ſhe ſearch'd for oftentimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Pillows where ſhe had put it. Her trouble appear'd ſo viſible one day to her Spies, that they had
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54982:20"/>the boldneſs to take away from her this Note, whilſt ſhe took ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and to put it into the hands of her Governeſs, who read what it contain'd, and made it be put in its place, for fear of increaſing her Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper. She went in the mean time to give an Account to the <hi>Queen,</hi> who complain'd of it to the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This prudent Monarch, fearing that if any Alliance of this conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſhould be made without the knowledge of the Princes who ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured his Court with their Children, they ſhould be ſcandalized at it, and recal them home, judg'd it proper to give notice to Prince <hi>Philip Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> his Father, and to the <hi>Admiral</hi> Father to <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> of the violent Inclination that they had one for the other. This Alliance being advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous for Prince <hi>Philip,</hi> his Anſwer was, That he would leave Heaven to act in it: and the <hi>Admiral</hi> not judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54982:21"/>that ſhe had provided for her ſelf to her advantage, he believ'd that it would be eaſie to divert this Inclination, in giving another Lover to his Daughter. He conjur'd then his Majeſty moſt humbly to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to recommend to her the old Duke of <hi>Alvaro,</hi> who was a Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly rich, and whom the fear to meet with a young Heart already diſpos'd of, hindred to declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to <hi>Iphigenia</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>King,</hi> inform'd of the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of theſe Princes, ſent afreſh to <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> to forbid him to ſee <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia,</hi> who was then abſolutely out of danger. The <hi>Queen</hi> undertook to prepare her to hearken favourably to the Duke of <hi>Alvaro.</hi> This love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Princeſs, who at firſt underſtood her Intention, told her Majeſty, That although it appear'd that nothing in the World ought to be freer than the Choice of a Husband, ſhe had ſo much Reſpect and Eſteem for the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54982:21"/>Lord that ſhe had propos'd to her, that ſhe would endeavour to fancy him 40 years younger, that ſhe might have more reaſon to love him. The <hi>Queen,</hi> who judg'd by this Anſwer, that it was not eaſie to perſwade a young Maid to love indifferently all ſorts of Objects, contented her ſelf with this beginning, and made the Amorous Old Man comprehend it would be a hard matter to ſurprize a place poſſeſs'd by a powerful Enemy: That he might nevertheleſs render his Aſſiduities to <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> and that he might put in practice all his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, to endeavour to make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf be beloved. The <hi>Duke,</hi> who was a little ſenſible of the weakneſs of Age, was not capable to remove ſo many Engines. He went the ſame Evening to the Queen's Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, where he had been inform'd <hi>Iphigenia</hi> would be; and it was in her Majeſties preſence that he made her his firſt Declarations. It is not to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54982:22"/>be believed how wittily this young <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> anſwer'd the old <hi>Count,</hi> and how ſhe made him flote between Hope and Deſpair. She droll'd a long time upon the difference of years, and ended at laſt with prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting that ſhe loved better a white and experienced Head, than a vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and well-made Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who conceiv'd that they had deſign'd this Old Man for her, was impatient to inform <hi>Alphonſus</hi> of this Comedy. But the promiſes ſhe had made to the <hi>Queen</hi> to think no more of him, and to have Eyes only for him that Heaven ſeem'd to have choſe for her by the hand of her Father, made her fear to renew with <hi>Alphonſus</hi> a new Commerce. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, ſhe run to the Houſe of the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> to whom ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the Adventure, and where ſhe writ theſe Lines, which ſhe left upon the Table of her Cabinet for her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:54982:22"/>
                  <head>The Letter of <hi>Iphigenia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THey would force me to love a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepid Old Man; as if Love ought to be enſlav'd by Intereſt. Teach me the Art to feign; for I aſſure you I am troubled to ſeem all Fire near a Froſt. The good man they propoſe to me, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons me his already. But after what a way does he make his Court? He enters, he kiſſes my Hand, he ſits over againſt me with his Face ſo near mine, that if he take not care, I ſhall ſome day by fetching my Breath with ſtrength, meet with his, and ſnatch from him his laſt Sigh. What a Sympathy of Humours, and what a Reſemblance of Complexions is here! They ſay he has need of four or five Blankets, beſides a ſuit of Furs, to keep him warm a Nights in the Month of</hi> July. <hi>I thank my Fate for furniſhing us with any Subject that may contribute to our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54982:23"/>divertiſement, when on the one ſide it deprives us of the ſatisfaction of ſeeing one another. If you are diſcreet and conſtant, none but you muſt pretend to my Eſteem. Beg of Love to furniſh us with ſome new Stratagem and ſure Means to put an end to our prohibition, and to content us. You know the hand of her that loves you. This ſuffices.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>As ſoon as <hi>Alphonſus</hi> entred the Houſe of the Princeſs his Siſter, <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia</hi> put him in mind of the place where he might find this Note. His meeting her, moderated his Sorrow; he read it over and over, with the greateſt ſatisfaction imaginable, and carried it away without having thought it neceſſary to make an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to it.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Lord <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varo</hi> gave no reſt to <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> he preſs'd her, he ſollicited her, he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd the Credit of all thoſe that had any power over the mind of this
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54982:23"/>
               <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> he offer'd her a thouſand Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of value, gave her Comedies, Balls, Serenades, treated magnificently on her account a party of the Ladies of the Court, went not from her houſe till it was very late, was at her Toilet, and perform'd admirably well all the Devoirs of a young Gallant; during which, ſhe rallied his Weakneſs: And <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who believ'd himſelf only beloved, publiſhed every-where, that he was collecting the Memoirs of what paſſed between the old <hi>Duke,</hi> and the lovely <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> to compile a <hi>Gallant Novel,</hi> which he would call, <hi>The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Gallant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Old Age is always diſtruſtful and ſuſpicious. The <hi>Duke</hi> maintain'd very many Perſons up and down to watch <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who inform'd him that he turn'd his Conduct into Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule, and that he endeavour'd to render him the Proverb of the Court. This Preſumption exaſperated the Old Man to ſuch a degree, that he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54982:24"/>reſolv'd to be reveng'd of him. If his Strength had been anſwerable to his Courage, he would not have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd any other Arm but his own to demand ſatisfaction of <hi>Alphonſus.</hi> Having one day met him two Leagues from the Town, following the firſt motions of his great Heart, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted from his Coach, and obliged <hi>Alphonſus</hi> to alight, with a reſolution to fight him, if Count <hi>Angelo,</hi> his Nephew, who was with him, had not taken his Uncles part, who was more than Threeſcore and fifteen years old, againſt a Prince that was hardly Nine and twenty.</p>
            <p>Theſe two young Lords having drawn their Swords, puſht for ſome time very vigorouſly. It was not the Dukes fault, that his Nephew, whom he animated by all powerful Exhortations, remain'd not Maſter of the Field. He was nevertheleſs wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, having receiv'd a very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Wound in the Arm, by which
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54982:24"/>he loſt very much Bloud. This ſad Spectacle, very far from cooling the Duke's Courage, inflam'd it more; he put himſelf in a poſture to ſecond the Wounded, when <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who was too brave to engage with une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual ſtrength, ſmiling, pray'd the <hi>Duke</hi> not to oblige him to do an Action which would be always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful to him, although even he ſhould have the better of it. Then remounting his Horſe, he return'd the ſame way towards the Town up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Hand-gallop. The noiſe of this Rancounter was ſpread abroad half an hour after, and came even to the Ears of the <hi>King,</hi> who gave command to <hi>Alphonſus</hi> to confine himſelf to his houſe, till new Orders.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia</hi> heard, almoſt at the ſame time, the ſucceſs of <hi>Alphonſus</hi> his Arms. Whatſoever inclination ſhe had for this Prince, ſhe could not but compaſſionate the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Fortune, whoſe Courage ſhe admir'd. She
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54982:25"/>took his part in ſome ſort alſo againſt this young Rival, becauſe that ſhe heard that he inſolently vaunted of his advantage; ſhe ſuffered with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret that a young man ſhould inſult over one of ſo great Age, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd for the <hi>Duke</hi> as high Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Eſteem, as ſhe had Love for <hi>Alphonſus.</hi> She receiv'd a Viſit from that Old Man that very ſame Evening, where he told her things that touch'd her very much.</p>
            <p>'Twas after a ſerious Converſation that ſhe had had with him, where he had painted out the Advantages ſhe might draw from her Alliance, that ſhe paſs'd a part of the Night in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating upon the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Propoſals. Amongſt other Reflections which ſhe made, ſhe conſidered that it would be always commendable to obey a Father who was more underſtanding in Affairs than her ſelf, and who only look'd after her Intereſts; that the Pleaſures of the Bed made not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54982:25"/>up the greateſt Delights of Life; that if ſhe taſted not preſently of thoſe Sweets which wiſe men accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but ſuperficial and imaginary, ſhe ſhould yet, after the death of a man within two inches of the Grave, in the middle of her Age, experience them; that <hi>Alphonſus</hi> paſs'd amongſt thoſe who kept him company, for a fantaſtick Spark, and raſh; and that it might be hazardous and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to ſacrifice her Liberty to a young man, who lov'd leſs on the account of Reaſon than Paſſion. Sleep having ſurpriz'd her in the midſt of theſe confuſed Thoughts, the firſt that poſſeſs'd her when ſhe was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, was to make tryal by Wit and Addreſs, of the true Temper of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus;</hi> whereby ſhe reſolv'd to ſound his Heart by an Artifice that I ſhall tell you, after that I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd the Diſcourſe which ſhe had that day during ſome hours with the <hi>Duke.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:54982:26"/>
            <p>She took a little reſt in the inner part of an Alcove, all alone. She was there reading ſome pages of a Romance which ſhe had in her hand, when the <hi>Old Duke</hi> was brought in to her Chamber. He ſate down by her, and diſcours'd with her of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different ſubjects, till ſhe fetcht a ſigh, which made the Converſation change. He took it for a token of the deſire ſhe had to hear him to ſpeak of other matters, and 'twas that made him begin in this ſort: <q>I know not, Madam, whether you have heard favourably the Declarations of Love that I have made you. I am perſwaded that you would be ſenſible of thoſe that ſhould be made you by Perſons of more merit and fewer years. It is true, that Youth has powerful Charms, and that old Age cannot but cauſe diſguſt to a young <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> accompliſh'd as you are; but it muſt alſo be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, that that has for its ſhare
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54982:26"/>Tranſports of Anger and Fury, and this, Prudence and good Conduct. It is true moreover, that the firſt joyns to external Charms the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties of Diſcourſe, and that the Language of the other is not very perſwaſive. Nevertheleſs, I have this advantage, Madam, above thoſe who may pretend to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Alliance, that if I explain my ſelf more plainly, I ſpeak with more ſincerity. You may believe beſides, that if it be my good Fortune to poſſeſs you, I will endow you with all the Eſtate which Birth and Fortune have heap'd upon me. I ſhould be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs in deſpair that the World ſhould one day reproach me with having done violence to your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination. You have in your young years more underſtanding than any Princeſs of this Court; and therefore you are of your ſelf capable of determining in an Affair
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54982:27"/>of this conſequence. As for the reſt, I can aſſure you, purſued he laughing, that againſt the cuſtom of thoſe of my years, I am neither troubleſome nor jealous.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who had till then kept ſilence through reſpect, anſwer'd the <hi>Duke</hi> with very much modeſty, <q>That ſhe would think upon the things which he had urg'd to her; that his Reaſons were very ſtrong; and that in a little time he ſhould know her Reſolution. That as for the reſt, ſhe was infinitely oblig'd to him for the choice that he was pleas'd to make of her, in the midſt of a Court where he might diſpoſe abſolutely of the Heart of the Faireſt and moſt Accompliſh'd of all thoſe Princeſſes that made up its Delights.</q> She pray'd him, purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to this Diſcourſe when he took leave of her, <q>to demand of the King the liberty of <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> which would not be refus'd him. I have
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54982:27"/>a ſtrong inclination, ſaid ſhe to him, to tax this Prince of Raſhneſs, to treat him with Haughtineſs, and to break off with him for ever, as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle regard as he has to the Leſſons I ſhall preſcribe him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Although this Intention to break with him was only conditional, the <hi>Duke,</hi> without troubling himſelf to dive into it, went to demand of the King <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s liberty, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat his Majeſty to permit him once more to ſee <hi>Iphigenia;</hi> which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving obtain'd from his Mercy, he went himſelf to aſſure <hi>Alphonſus</hi> of the King's favour, to conjure him to forget what was paſt, and to inform him that the Princeſs <hi>Iphigenia</hi> deſired to ſee him.</p>
            <p>This Prince was very much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd at the Advances of the <hi>Duke,</hi> which made him ſuſpicious of ſome Stratagem that he was contriving againſt him. Nevertheleſs, he thank'd him handſomly for the good Offices
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54982:28"/>that he had juſt then done him, and promis'd to go to receive the Orders, of the <hi>Dutcheſs.</hi> He went to her Houſe two hours after, and <hi>Iphigenia</hi> was no ſooner inform'd of his arrival, but ſhe diſmiſt the Company that was with her.</p>
            <p>The love which ſhe had had for this Prince, and which was not yet extinguiſh'd in her Heart, made her ſeem to feel very much joy at his return: <q>Come, ſaid ſhe to him, ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, wicked man, I have many things to tell you. Prepare your ſelf to hear ſuch as will be diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to you.</q> To which <hi>Alphonſus</hi> reply'd, <q>A tender Princeſs cannot ſpeak harſh things; and were I as culpable as I am faithful, you could not ſo handle me, that your Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications would be of force to make me repent of my Crime, becauſe you would mortifie me with ſo good a grace, that I ſhould always eſteem my ſelf Innocent. You are
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54982:28"/>too preſumptious, added <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> and I believe you will change your mind at the Propoſitions I have to make you. You may try me, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, purſued he, as much as you pleaſe; I flatter my ſelf to be able to juſtifie what I have ſaid. Very well, continued the Dutcheſs, ſince you have ſo ſtrong a Wit, and that I ſee you arm'd againſt all ſorts of Attaques, ſit you down there, and delay not to anſwer me.</q> They had no ſooner taken Seats, but ſhe ſaid to him, <q>The buſineſs is, my Lord <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus,</hi> that you give your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that I become your Rival's Wife. I believe I need not tell you that the Admiral is a man ſolid and intereſſed, who will never conſent to our Alliance; that he will make me marry the Duke <hi>Alvero,</hi> whoſe great Wealth is able to uphold our Family; and that the King will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to no other Match. Let me then do a thing againſt my Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54982:29"/>Permit me to put a man in his Grave that cannot live longer almoſt, that we may be in a better condition to paſs our live times hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily and quietly. You need not doubt but to find me always the ſame in Body and in Mind. Thus I do not properly break with you, I only propoſe a delay that may laſt but a very little time.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Although it is true that <hi>Alphonſus</hi> did not expect a Complement of this nature, having a little conſulted with himſelf, and appear'd for ſome time thoughtful, believing himſelf baniſh'd from the Heart of <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> he would ſhew her that he was as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different as ſhe was changeable, and 'twas that which put this Anſwer in his mouth. <q>Are theſe, Madam, the Promiſes of an inviolable Fidelity. Have you ſo ſoon forgot the mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Proteſtations which we have made? Can I believe that you have lov'd, ſince you now ceaſe from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54982:29"/>loving? What can I hope from a Flame which is extinguiſh'd in the heat of its vigour? No, Madam, I cannot, without dying, ſee you in the Arms of a Rival, if you do not promiſe me that the Marriage which you are contriving ſhall only ſerve as a Vail to the Favours which you will grant me.</q> 
               <hi>Alphonſus</hi> thought he might very well inſult over the Princeſs's Vertue, ſince ſhe ſeem'd to have no more love for him. <hi>Iphige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> offended at ſo inſolent an Anſwer, diſſembled then and reply'd nothing, only that he ſhould have cauſe to praiſe her Fidelity. They parted thereupon diſſatisfied with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, inſomuch that ſome Servants perceiv'd that <hi>Alphonſus</hi> ſhook his head, and muttered between his teeth at the foot of the great Stair-caſe.</p>
            <p>After ſo ſurpriſing a Propoſal, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> abated much in the Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Eſteem which he had for the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> who became almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54982:30"/>to him; and <hi>Iphigenia</hi> after a Propoſition ſo offenſive, ſhew'd her coldneſs to <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who did all he could to turn the <hi>Duke en Ridicule,</hi> and to render the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Court-Raillery, He com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd Verſes for this effect which he ſpread every-where, under an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Name, wherein he deſcrib'd the ridiculous Fires of an Old Man and the Infidelity of his Miſtriſs. Here is a Copy of them, agreeable to the Original.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="epigram">
                        <head>Upon an Old Man in love with an Inconſtant Princeſs.</head>
                        <head type="sub">An EPIGRAM.</head>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>A Duke, within two inches of the Grave,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>His Head with Snow quite cover'd o're,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>To carry on a new Amout,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes all means the Fair One to engage.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54982:30"/>
                           <l>
                              <hi>This Candle that's juſt ready to expire,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Is in a Dutcheſs's falſe Heart</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Worthily ſuffered to have part,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Who does againſt his liberty conſpire.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>She by this means has all her Heart can wiſh;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>For Death the Duke will ſoon remove,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And then this Weather-cock of Love,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Who change affects, will chuſe another Diſh.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe Verſes made noiſe enough to come to the knowledge of the <hi>Duke,</hi> and of her who was made the ſubject of them; upon which ſhe threatned <hi>Alphonſus</hi> to play him an ill trick for it: he betrayed the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret which he owed to <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s truſt in him, and manifeſted his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, in making the Letter publick; wherein this poor Lady declaim'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rigour of Deſtiny, which ordain'd for her an impotent Old Man. <hi>Iphigenia</hi> outrag'd at ſuch a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54982:31"/>proceeding, went to complain to the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who told her, <q>That ſhe ought to have known better <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s humour, before ſhe had truſted him; that he was the moſt giddy-headed Lover in the World, and a young man without diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who conſidered not, provided he could divert himſelf, at whoſe coſt it were; that ſhe was in the ſame apprehenſion on the ſcore of ſuch a like indiſcreet Spark, to whom ſhe had entruſted ſomething which ſhe would very fain keep ſecret; that it was not very difficult to make this Letter paſs for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit; and that as to the reſt, ſhe ſhould refer her ſelf to common Report; that Calumny was the Vice of Courts, and that ſhe ſhould be before aſſur'd of the truth of the Fact, from his own Confeſſion, who had been accounted the Author of the Report.</q> 
               <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who reliſh'd theſe Reaſons, repreſented to the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54982:31"/>Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> that to tax <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> of it, were to expoſe her ſelf to new Railleries; that he would be cunning enough to deny the thing, and malicious enough to adde Satyr upon Satyr, and to divert himſelf with her Fears.</p>
            <p>Whilſt our intimate Princeſſes were deliberating together of the means to avoid hazarding themſelves with <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> in extorting the truth from him, the <hi>Duke</hi> came to pay a Viſit to the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> with whom he hop'd to find <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who made her the Repoſitary of all her Secerets. He entred, they diſcours'd for ſome time together, every one was in a good humour, when the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion having turn'd upon the Chapter of the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Marriage with <hi>Iphige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> the Old Man to whom ſhe had as it were engag'd her Faith, told her, <q>That he was too much her Friend, and too ſincere to conceal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing from her.</q> And drew a
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54982:32"/>Paper out of his Pocket which was an exact Copy of the Letter which we have been ſpeaking of, wherein <hi>Iphigenia</hi> ſhew'd her averſion for the <hi>Duke,</hi> on the back of which <hi>Alphonſus</hi> his Verſes were written.</p>
            <p>The reading of the Epigram in the firſt place, mortifi'd <hi>Iphigenia</hi> in the higheſt degree. But that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded her, was the ſhock which that Letter gave her, which Love had heretofore dictated to her, and which Treachery had now made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. The Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> who ſaw her in this perplexity, drew her out of trouble, in making pleaſant Reflections upon that Letter. <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia</hi> believing it would be to her advantage to turn the buſineſs into Raillery, grew pleaſant in her turn, and own to the <hi>Duke,</hi> 
               <q>That ſhe was the Author of that Letter; that in reality, the firſt propoſal that had been made her of an Alliance with him, had made her wild at the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54982:32"/>time that ſhe had an Inclination for <hi>Alphonſus:</hi> But that this fault ought to be forgiven her; that it was a proof of her Conſtancy and Fidelity; that having never had the honour to have been in his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, ſhe had given way too much to the Impreſſion which his Age made on her Spirit; and that as the Fire which is difficult to be kindled, is likewiſe difficult to be extinguiſh'd, the greater Averſion ſhe had for him before ſhe knew him, the greater Eſteem ſhe had conceiv'd for him ſince ſhe had known him, and that this Eſteem ſhould never be blotted out.</q> She ſpoke too well, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended her ſelf with too much Wit, not to obtain her Pardon. The Old Man tore the Letter, and diſcours'd no more of any thing, but of demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſatisfaction from <hi>Alphonſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They might freely conſult of the means to be reveng'd of him in the preſence of the Princeſs his Siſter.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54982:33"/>For beſides that ſhe lov'd him not, the hopes to become the onely Heireſs of her Family, made her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire his death. They concluded then that the Count St. <hi>Angelo,</hi> the <hi>Duke</hi>'s Nephew, ſhould challenge <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> and that they ſhould decide to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the difference that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them. <q>I will go ſend for him this Evening, ſaid the Old Man; you will inſpire him with a Spirit of Revenge; and although I eſteem him valiant, I doubt not but he will become a hundred times fiercer, when you ſhall your ſelf have put your Intereſts into his hands. It will be an honour to fall in my ſervice, and in the Quarrel of that Perſon whom I moſt honour.</q> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to this Promiſe, the <hi>Duke</hi> withdrew, and left the two confident Princeſſes at liberty to reſume their Converſation.</p>
            <p>They judg'd it convenient, after ſome deliberation, to ſend for <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus,</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:54982:33"/>who came to them an hour after. The Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> as ſoon as he was ſate down, began to ſpeak, by asking him, when he would give over abuſing his Relations, and when he would leave the World in Repoſe. He was going to reply ſomething, when <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> impatient, without any tranſport of Anger, call'd him Perfidious, and put into his hands the pieces of the Copy of the Letter which had been torn but a little before. This Letter was ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers'd, that he knew not the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Perſon who had tranſcrib'd it. He pretended to be ignorant of what it was, and employ'd above half an hour in ſeeming to fit again the pieces of Paper, though he ſtill plac'd them wrong. <hi>Iphigenia</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that he miſtook on purpoſe, took the pieces again out of his hand, and told him, that they contain'd the Copy of a Letter which ſhe had through confidence writ to him:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:54982:34"/>That ſhe could never have thought that he had been ſo baſe to divulge it, and to employ his Pen in compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the moſt bloudy Railleries that could be read. That it could never be any Credit for him to be reveng'd after ſo baſe a manner, of a Perſon whoſe tender Sentiments he had not been acquainted with. <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> counterfeiting aſtoniſhment, ſeem'd to underſtand nothing of <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s diſcourſe, and thereupon ſhe her ſelf fitted the pieces of the Letter, ſo that they might be read. He ſwore after a great exclamation, that that Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery ſhould coſt the Keeper of his Wardrobe his Life. That that Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had been ſtollen out of his Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket; that he would puniſh the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Author of this Crime, and proteſted that for his part he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent of what he was accuſed of. His Hypocriſie was too viſible: His Excuſes were not at all receiv'd, and he endeavour'd in vain to juſtifie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54982:34"/>There was no Trick which he made not uſe of, to diſſwade <hi>Iphigenia</hi> even to the ſhedding of Tears: He threw himſelf on his Knees, and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her Pardon for a Fault which he would efface with the Bloud of any Man, and for the expiation of which, he would voluntarily give his own, were he guilty of it. <q>'Tis not that which I demand, ſaid <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> you will never kill the guilty; if you ſpare him who terms himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, we expected ſuch-like Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifications. Know that I ſolemnly retract the Word that I have given you. Take what's paſs'd for a Foolery; you ſhall know towards the Evening the cauſe for which I have intreated you to come hither. To morrow you — She was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on further,</q> when the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina</hi> having pull'd her by the Arm, made her ſtop there. <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> who underſtood by half a word what ſhe was about to ſay, roſe up
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54982:35"/>as ſoon as ſhe was ſilent, and ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the company, told her, <hi>To morrow, Madam, to morrow whatever you pleaſe.</hi> He thereupon withdrew and was juſt getting into his Coach, when the <hi>Count de St. Angelo</hi> entred. This Rencounter made him ſuſpect that it was he with whom they threatned him. But he was in no great trouble, and he went home to expect with patience what was meant by that word, <hi>To morrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Angelo</hi> had ſcarce preſented himſelf before theſe Princeſſes, when <hi>Iphigenia</hi> ſaid to him, <q>I doubt not, Sir, but you are already inform'd what I demand from your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Friendſhip; you know how <hi>Alphonſus</hi> has offended me, and how much the Duke has reaſon to complain of him: The buſineſs is to demand ſatisfaction of this inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Prince. He is valiant, and will accept all Challenges. If my Intereſts affect you, you will not
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:54982:35"/>be troubled that I have made choice of you as of an undaunted Lord, whoſe Courage is univerſally known. Are you diſpos'd to ſecond my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and to fight for the Duke's Honour. I am fully reſolved of it, Madam, reply'd the Count, if you do me right, you ought to be perſwaded of it, before I aſſure you of it. Prince <hi>Alphonſus</hi> uſes you after a very uncivil manner. All the Court blames him, and will without doubt approve the deſign which you project with Juſtice, and which I ſhall endeavour to execute with all the Ardour I am capable of. After whatever manner things go, whoſe ſucceſs we cannot fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee, purſued <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> I ſhall be ſenſibly indebted to you all my Life. Send then this Evening to advertiſe <hi>Alphonſus</hi> to meet you to morrow with his Piſtol, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd with his Second, between the hours of Seven and Eight, at a
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54982:36"/>place which you ſhall appoint him. You ſhall find at your Lodging, at the time appointed, the Perſon who will be your Second.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This was enough for Count <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelo,</hi> who, beſides theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, had on his own ſcore Reaſons for Enmity againſt the Prince <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus,</hi> with whom he had a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times ſought an occaſion of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling. He took leave of the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes,</hi> after he had teſtified very civilly to the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> that he had the greateſt Obligations in the World to her, that ſhe had judg'd him worthy to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain her quarrel. <hi>Iphiginia</hi> at laſt took leave of the Princeſs, to whom ſhe ſaid, That ſhe was going to think of a Comrade for St. <hi>Angelo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This generous Maid (who had more Courage than is uſually found in her Sex) believ'd ſhe could not find any Perſon whatſoever that could revenge her Honour with more Valour than her ſelf. Arm'd with
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:54982:36"/>the reſolution of a <hi>Heroine,</hi> ſhe ſent to borrow the Habit of a Cavalier, which ſhe put on the next day. She provided a Caſe of Piſtols, of which ſhe made tryal, and took Coach ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Morning, accompany'd only with a Gentleman Uſher, who imagined nothing elſe, but that ſhe was going to ſome Hunting Match, whom ſhe diſmiſs'd as ſoon as ſhe was alighted at the Count of St. <hi>Angelo</hi>'s Lodgings.</p>
            <p>That Count, who immediately knew her in this Equipage, was very much ſurpriz'd when ſhe told him the reſolution ſhe had of demanding ſatisfaction her ſelf of her Treacherous Gallant. He endeavour'd by all the preſſings Reaſons in the World, to make her alter her thoughts. But he found ſo much oppoſition on her part, and ſo much eagerneſs, that he was flatter'd with the hopes of ſeeing her a Conquerour. They both eat a light Breakfaſt, equipped themſelves, moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54982:37"/>on Horſeback, and went to the place appointed, where <hi>Alphonſus</hi> was before them half a quarter of an hour.</p>
            <p>As far off as <hi>Iphigenia</hi> could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern him, ſhe took her Piſtol in her hand, and made him a ſignal to make ready, not being willing to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by all the common Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, for fear of being known. But <hi>Alphonſus</hi> cry'd out, that that was not the cuſtom here; that they ought not to fight without agreeing before on what Conditions. Then they approached each other, and St. <hi>Angelo</hi> having ſhew'd <hi>Alphonſus</hi> the unknown Cavalier who was to fight with him, he ſo attentively conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Face of the Perſon would duel him, that he knew <hi>Iphigenia</hi> under her diſguiſe. He then chang'd Colour, and our <hi>Dutcheſs Cavalier</hi> having obſerv'd it, levell'd her Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol at him: He eſcap'd the ſhot of her Piſtol, and having ſhot off his into the Air, he cry'd out, <q>What is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54982:37"/>it you, adorable Dutcheſs! is it you that would take away my life? If I have merited Death, I conſent to loſe it, and that you ſhould take it from me, without diſputing it with you. It will be always glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious for me to fall under the ſtroaks of a Heroine.</q> 
               <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> incens'd then, replied, <q>No, Ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, I have not ſo mean a Soul, as thou haſt a perfidious Heart. How thirſty ſoever I am for thy Bloud, I am not reſolv'd to drink it, until I have juſtly ſpilt it. Defend thy ſelf like a gallant man; and if thou haſt any Eſteem for me, either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive me of Life, or furniſh me with fair means to take it away from thee.</q>
            </p>
            <p>How great a mind ſoever our <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazon</hi> made appear to fight, ſhe could never obtain from <hi>Alphonſus</hi> the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which ſhe deſired. The Seconds, after their Example, would not diſcharge; and <hi>Alphonſus</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54982:38"/>to them, that they could not gain Honour in a Combat ſo ſingular. Our Illuſtrious <hi>Heroine</hi> did an Act which would have been blamed in any other but a Woman; for hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away by her ſpight, having clapp'd the muzxle of her Piſtol to <hi>Alphonſus'</hi> Horſe's head, ſhe ſhot three Bullets into it, wherewith he fell un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Cavalier that rid him. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> could not ſave himſelf, in the fall, from a Sinew-ſtrain, wherewith he was incommoded a long time. As ſoon as he was on the ground, he laugh'd and ſaid calmly to the <hi>Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs, You have diſmounted me, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, you have bore away the honour of the Combat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There paſs'd nothing more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable in this occaſion; each one return'd Home; and this Expedition was immediately divulg'd at Court, where ſhe was call'd no more the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> but the <hi>Handſom Cavalier.</hi> The Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> whom <hi>Iphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:54982:38"/>had not pre-acquainted with her deſign of diſguiſing her ſelf, was extreamly ſurpriz'd when ſhe heard what had paſs'd. She was ſo impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to hear the recital of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture from the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi>'s own mouth, that ſhe went to her Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to ſee her as ſoon as ſhe had an incling of it. She immediately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended her for the greatneſs of her Soul, and her undauntedneſs, and at laſt conjured her to make her a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Action. She inform'd her of all the Circumſtances of it, and was ſtill diſcourſing with her on that ſubject, when <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who was unwilling to be ſeen, entred the Houſe by the Garden-gate, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended by the back Stairs to the Chamber where they were. <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> who had ſeen him croſs a little Court, run to acquaint the <hi>Princeſſes</hi> with his Arrival, ſo that <hi>Iphigenia</hi> had had time to hide her ſelf behind the Hangings, from whence ſhe could
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54982:39"/>hear the Converſation of the <hi>Princeſs</hi> and <hi>Alphonſus</hi> her Brother. He ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected that his Siſter would have the curioſity to learn the Hiſtory of the deſign'd Combat. He told it her like a Cavalier, he extoll'd at firſt <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s Courage, whom he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards call'd a Raſh Woman. As he was beginning to grow hot upon her account, ſhe could forbear no longer: She came out from the place where ſhe was hidden, and ſaid to him fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <q>If it is true that I have wanted Conduct, it hath been becauſe I have ſpar'd a Coward who did not deſerve to live. But it is no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; it is more glorious to conquer ones Reſentments than to let it break out. I have ſhew'd you, that I am ſenſible of the Injuries. If I have preſerv'd your Life, when at the hazard of ſome light Reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, I could have taken it from you; I may ſay, that I have given you it to leave you time to repent
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:54982:39"/>of your Ingratitude, and that you may be puniſh'd as often as you ſee her whom you have ſo baſely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray'd.</q> 
               <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> whom the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected preſence of <hi>Iphigenia</hi> had not a little ſurpriz'd, was much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, to reply to the harſh things which ſhe had ſaid to him. He no more juſtifi'd himſelf, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to reply to her, <q>Yes, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, I owe you my life, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you have ſpar'd it, only to publiſh your generoſity. I will own freely to you, that the Paſſion to which your Charms had given birth, hath not been able to brook a Rival. In effect, Madam, was it not a very hard thing, to have been able to boaſt of having been heard favourably by the moſt Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd Princeſs of <hi>Europe,</hi> to have been congratulated a thouſand times by all the Court for this Honour, to have acted nothing that I know of which hath blemiſhed the profound
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54982:40"/>Reſpect that is due to her divine Qualities, and nevertheleſs, to ſee ones ſelf forc'd to give conſent that another ſhould enjoy a Beauty for which one had ſigh'd all his Life. They are theſe Conſiderations, and this Pill ſo hard to ſwallow, that hath made me forget my ſelf. Hence our breach of Friendſhip began: Theſe in fine, are the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that have brought things to the extremity in which they are. What, interrupted <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> is it not then permitted to put a Lover to the Tryal? Ought you to take things in a wrong ſence? My ways of indifference ought, inſtead of cooling, to animate your Purſuits. I pretended to flie, and you have immediately forſaken me. What Zeal, what Ardour, or rather what weak and feeble Paſſion, it is then when I ſeem'd to eſcape from you, that you ſhould ſignalize your Love. You ought to pray, conjure,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:54982:40"/>and fix by your Fidelity, my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Inconſtancy: You ought to be more aſſiduous, to write Elegies, to ſigh, and ſhed Tears.</q>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>When a ſtrong Paſſion doth Mens Hearts inſpire,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And they a tempting Beauty do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They ſigh, look pale, and languiſh with deſire;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But you nor ſigh, or languiſh any more.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>As there is nothing ſo Eloquent as a witty Woman in Love, <hi>Iphigenia</hi> had never appear'd to Prince <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> ſo Eloquent as that very day. After he had heard her, he threw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at her Feet, and with Tears in his Eyes, cry'd out, <q>Pardon, Divine Dutcheſs, pardon. You are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and I am culpable; I will ſhut my Eyes to all that may make me queſtion your Fidelity. How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54982:41"/>ſhould I be, if you were ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent as to account of what is paſt as a Dream! How ſhould I bleſs my Stars, if I could yet enter again into your favour! Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Madam, what puniſhment you pleaſe for the expiation of my Crime. There is none ſo rigorous, to which I will not ſubmit: There is nothing that I will not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take and perform, if you aſſure me of my Pardon.</q> He ſpoke from the bottom of his heart, and his Sighs were ſuch infallible Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of it, that <hi>Iphigenia</hi> was molli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied at the ſight of his ſubmiſſions. If he wept, ſhe ſhed Tears; ſo that their common Grief became of that character which Violence renders dumb. She recover'd her ſelf at laſt, and permitted him to pretend to be ſtill belov'd.</p>
            <p>The Quarrels of Lovers are oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Motives to, and Renewings of Love. <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> after this humble
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54982:41"/>ſatisfaction from <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> lov'd him in appearance more tenderly than ever, at leaſt he flatter'd himſelf ſo. He ſuffered himſelf to be ſo ſtrongly pre-poſſeſs'd with this opinion, that there was not a day paſt, but he vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited her at the <hi>Princeſs</hi> her Siſters Lodgings, whither ſhe went every day. Nevertheleſs, he was too much loſt in her favour, to be ſo eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh'd there. A Paſſion extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd, is ſeldom reviv'd in a witty Womans Heart, and thoſe of that character hardly forget the reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Injuries once receiv'd. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> his Treaſon had made a deep impreſſion in <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s mind, and wrought unanimouſly with certain natural motions, which will grow more ſenſible in the concluſion to render him the Object of her Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alphonſus</hi> was alone in the Kings Chamber, when News was brought to his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> that the Duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varo</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:54982:42"/>who had withdrawn two days ſince to his Caſtle ſix Leagues from the City, died ſuddenly that very day. He thought that at the recital of this News he might judge of the Dutcheſs's Inclination on his account. He went to her Lodgings at the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary time, where he found the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes</hi> conferring together. He medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated ſometime upon the Air that he ſhould affect, and what courſe he ſhould take to acquaint them with what he had newly learnt. <hi>Iphige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> obſerving him more ſilent than ordinary, asked him, What cauſe could render him ſo melancholy, him whom all the World commended for his good humour. <q>I am trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, replied he, at a Loſs which all the Court ſhould be ſenſible of, and which will, I make no queſtion, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict you. The Duke of <hi>Alvaro</hi> is dead this morning in the Caſtle which bears his Name. I have learnt the News of it from the ſame
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:54982:42"/>Courrier which hath brought it to his Majeſty.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Iphigenia</hi> had never had much inclination for that Lord, or that ſhe would diſſemble to make good a Fidelity which was but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to Prince <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> ſhe ſeem'd not to be much troubled for his Death, ſhe only ſaid, That Count St. <hi>Angelo</hi>'s Nephew, who was his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Heir, would be a good Match, and that though he were not handſome, the great Eſtate which was fallen to him, would very much adorn him. That was all that was ſaid then on the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the Deceas'd, in whom <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> loſt the greateſt, but not the moſt to be fear'd, of his Rivals.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Prince,</hi> who whilſt the late <hi>Duke</hi> courted <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> with appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation had had all ſort of acceſs to her, fear'd that his Majeſty, at the Queens ſollicitation, might renew his former Prohibitions to him not to ſee her. He prevented her, and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54982:43"/>conjured his Goodneſs to permit him to render his Aſſiduities to that <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> ſince he preſum'd the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral</hi> the Dutcheſs's Father would no more reject his Alliance. The <hi>King</hi> having learnt that the <hi>Admiral</hi> left to his Daughter the abſolute li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the choice of a Husband, gratified <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s Requeſt, ſo that he ſpent every Afternoon with his Miſtriſs.</p>
            <p>About that time there arriv'd at the Court two young <hi>Princes</hi> from the Borders of <hi>Italy,</hi> Twins, very well made as to their Perſons, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make a great Figure. They made themſelves preſently eminent by their Magnificence, and took a pride in converſing with the moſt Witty of the Court-Ladies. The Dutcheſs, <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s Miſtriſs, was continually viſited by the younger, who had as much Briskneſs, and as little Judgment, as his elder Brother, who courted the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:54982:43"/>had Wit and Fineneſs of Thought.</p>
            <p>Although this young Prince fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented <hi>Iphigenia</hi> only to paſs away ſome agreeable moments, without carrying his deſires further, <hi>Alphonſus</hi> took <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage</hi> at it, and labour'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſo ſtrong a Jealouſie, that he fell ſick upon it. The <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> aſſur'd him, what ſhe could, that ſhe found nothing amiable in that <hi>Neopolitan;</hi> that onely complaiſance, and the thoughts that he would quickly leave the Court, made her approve of his Viſits. Her abſence from the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Houſe, whither ſhe went every day before the arrival of thoſe Princes, and the whole After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noons which ſhe gave to the Charms of that ſtrange Prince's Converſation, made him fear all, from the familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which begun to be between them. He proceeded ſo far, that one day he had the confidence to ask him, If he caſt his Eyes on the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> and if he pretended to her Alliance? To
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54982:44"/>whom the Prince anſwer'd. That he was not yet ſufficiently acquainted with Madam <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> to diſcover whether ſhe would receive Addreſſes of Love from him; but that he would attempt to puſh on his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. This Anſwer threw <hi>Alphonſus</hi> into a fearful Melancholly. All things ſeem'd to him to concur to deſtroy him in the Breaſt of that Fair One; and he really believ'd, by the coldneſs which ſhe expreſs'd to him, that her Inclinations were only for the Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. That handſome <hi>Neopolitan</hi> judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well by <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s Demand, who had ever <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s Name in his Mouth, that he courted this Dutcheſs, jeſted at it the very firſt Viſit that he made her. He made a deſcription to her of this Lover's Paſſion, under a young Lord's name with whom he ſaid he was acquainted at <hi>Venice;</hi> and being intreated to tell his Name to the whole Company, he ſooner hit upon that of his Miſtriſs than his,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54982:44"/>which he was never able to call to mind; which made the Dutcheſs tell him, That he ſhould have imprinted it ſtronger in his mind; but that ſhe believed the greateſt part of the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories which were related of ſuch A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, were a little fabulous. <q>I daily read ſome of this nature, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued ſhe, to which I can hardly give credit. Here the <hi>Neopolitan</hi> reply'd, It is true, Madam, that the Poets have ſeign'd ſuch like Paſſions: But Hiſtory will furniſh us with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity of undoubted Examples in the moſt famous Perſons of Antiquity. Have we not ſeen one of the <hi>Cato</hi>'s forget what he was, and enter into an Alliance with a Maid who had neither Riches nor Birth? Did not <hi>Piſiſtratus,</hi> the <hi>Athenian</hi> Tyrant, marry a Country Girl? What did not <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great for <hi>Flora?</hi> Did not <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> after fifty Battles won, yield to the Charms of a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>virca?</hi> The Hiſtory of the Death
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54982:45"/>of <hi>Anthony,</hi> who lov'd <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> is ſufficiently known to you. Did not the Conqueror of <hi>Aſia</hi> love exceſſively that <hi>Campaſpe</hi> whom for the overcoming of himſelf, he gave to the famous Painter <hi>Apelles?</hi> To what ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions did not the Charms <hi>Polioratia</hi> reduce <hi>Philip?</hi> without ſpeaking of the impreſſion which the Beauty of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ria</hi>'s Wife made upon the Royal Prophets heart.</q> Who does not— He was going on ſtill to lay open the like Litanies, and as impertinently, when the Dutcheſs interrupting him, told him, <q>I know not what he has not done, nor the truth of theſe Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories at the bottom; but of what I know, and of which I am fully convinc'd, is, that you have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent memory, and that there is never a Pedant in all this Kingdom, that dare diſpute with you the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of having heap'd up more words in his Head. Have you never heard that the like Paſſions are common
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54982:45"/>to the <hi>Monomotapoez,</hi> and the <hi>Topi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nambri?</hi> added ſhe. Are there Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Sir, as fooliſh as Men on this account?</q> This young Lord not having the wit to find out the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Raillery upon his inclination to ſhew his Reading, fell a laughing, and continued his Diſcourſe by an innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration as fit to be laugh'd at. <q>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſaid he, Madam, are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from this Weakneſs; and if I remember, <hi>Phaedra</hi> lov'd <hi>Hippolitus</hi> even to exceſs: <hi>Atalanta, Hippoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes; Galathea, Atis; Egeria, Numa; Circe, Glauchus; Penelopo; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes; Hypſicrata, Mithridates; Portia, Brutus; Julia, Pompey; Phocris, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetus.</hi>
               </q> He ſtopt, and would have ſtaid there, when <hi>Iphigenia</hi> roſe up, took a Book which lay upon the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and having open'd it, ſaid to him, <q>Liſten, Sir; you know not yet all this Romance by heart, you forget that <hi>Semiramis</hi> lov'd <hi>Ninus</hi> exceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; <hi>Biblis,</hi> her Brother; <hi>Mirra,</hi> her
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54982:46"/>Father; <hi>Calphurnia, Appian; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilia, Lucullus;</hi> and others yet, with which theſe two Pages are full. But let us return, I beſeech you, ſaid ſhe, to our firſt diſcourſe. On what occaſion have you made ſo many fine Remarks? On a Prince's occaſion who adores you, reply'd he, and is horribly melancholy, becauſe I take the freedom to come to you ſo often to pay you my Reſpects: On <hi>Alphonſus</hi> his occaſion, the moſt paſſionate, and the moſt jealous of all your Lovers. How! purſued ſhe, does that Prince love me at the coſt of his Reaſon? I can hardly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf, that ſo prudent a Lord cannot put bounds to Paſſion. Let us experiment what you ſay, and to that end do you meet me to morrow at the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina</hi>'s Houſe, and put him inſenſibly upon this Chapter, and endeavour to railly him ſo fiercely that his Jealouſie may ſerve for Divertiſement to the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54982:46"/>Circle which we ſhall form. Do you make upon him the Epitaph of a Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous man.</q> This young Lord, who had not yet gained experience enough of the World, to foreſee that he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf to become the May-game of others, promiſed the <hi>Dutcaeſs</hi> to prepare himſelf upon that ſubject, and withdrew very well content with that Propoſal, and with himſelf.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Iphigenia</hi> went the ſame Evening to diſcourſe with the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> whom ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to agree to a Comedy the next day at her houſe, where a young indiſcreet Spark and a jealous Lover would appear upon the Stage: After that, ſhe told her all that was paſs'd, and ask'd her if the eldeſt of the two Brothers <hi>Manfeldi,</hi> made her no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſals, as the Report went, <q>He has, reply'd the Princeſs, and ſuch preſſing ones, that it is almoſt no more time to act the Indifferent, without abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely diſcouraging him; which I
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54982:47"/>ſhould be averſe from doing, for the reaſons of good Breeding, although I have but little inclination for him. When he ſees me not, I am peſtered with his Letters. He hath gained, through his liberality, all my Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks even to <hi>Cornelia,</hi> and all the World will implant tenderneſs in me for that young Prince. I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that he has Wit, and very ſine Qualities: but in fine, there is not <hi>I know not what,</hi> which captivates; and I cannot believe that ever he will obtain me with my good will. When the Fancy takes me to marry, I will make choice of a Prince in whom nothing ſhall be wanting that may render him infinitely lovely to me, and worthy to be beloved eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,</q> I ſhould be of your Taſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted <hi>Iphigenia</hi> in this place, <q>if Marriage could charm me; and if I am not deceiv'd, I know a <hi>Prince</hi> who hath all that you can deſire: He loves you, he adores you, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54982:47"/>bears you ſo deep a Reſpect, that he durſt not diſcover his Paſſion; and if it does bring him to you one day, it will not be till he ſhall ſee you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to love.</q> What is he, reply'd immediately the Princeſs, <q>can I love an unknown perſon?</q> She had ſcarce made an end of ſpeaking, when <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> entring the Chamber, diverted their diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia</hi> had no ſooner perceiv'd him, than ſhe told him laughing, <q>Poor jealous Creature, they endeavour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready at your Epitaph; you are a dead man, if we may believe the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian <hi>Cadet.</hi> You have a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Rival in him, who will give you no repoſe. You will be put to the Teſt to morrow. Prepare your ſelf to ſuſtain a thouſand fine At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks, for the Enemy who is to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage you, has an infinite ſtock of Wit.</q> 
               <hi>Alphonſus</hi> taking the word here, ſaid, <q>It is then. Madam, ſince he hath the honour to frequent you,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54982:48"/>that he hath gain'd it. You are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fit to have communicated it to him. Raillery apart, Prince, added <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> the youngeſt of our <hi>Neopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litans</hi> will make you paſs for a jealous Perſon. He came to me upon your account to relate a Hiſtory the moſt ſilly in the World, which was follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with very many other things yet more ridiculous. He is a young man juſt come from the Univerſity, of a good memory, but wanting yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and underſtanding. He is a preſumptuous Novice, who thinks himſelf ignorant of nothing. In fine, he is a pretended Droll, who to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row will turn you into Ridicule. We will divert our ſelves with his Boyiſhneſs and Extravagances. Fail not to come hither to morrow after Dinner. You ſhall ſuffer him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to diſcourſe, and lead him inſenſibly to the ſubject that I will put on foot. Pray, above all things, do not drive him to a nonplus, but
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54982:48"/>rather ſeem to like of all that he ſhall offer to your conſideration.</q> 
               <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> to whom what was ſaid, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd his ordinary Tranquillity, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd to execute all that was ordered him by the <hi>Dutcheſs.</hi> He was about to withdraw the moſt ſatisfied of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, when the eldeſt of the <hi>Neopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> ſent to ask if the Princeſs <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> might be viſited. He came too ſeaſonably not to be admitted. Our two Princeſſes intreated <hi>Alphonſus</hi> to keep them company a little longer, but he begg'd them to diſpenſe with him, under pretext of having buſineſs of the greateſt conſequence. The <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opolitan</hi> meeting him upon the Stair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, complemented him, and told him, That he was very unhappy not to have come ſooner, becauſe he ſhould have had the advantage of his Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation for ſome time. <hi>Alphonſus</hi> made anſwer to his Civility, and intreated him to put off the Match to the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that ſome perſons would form
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54982:49"/>a Circle at his Siſters, where he ſhould meet him without fail. Then they took leave of one another, after having conteſted to whom the upper hand ſhould be given at parting.</p>
            <p>The Lover of the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina</hi> had acquired Acquaintance ſufficient with her, not longer to be oblig'd to all thoſe ſuperſtitious Formalities which are obſerv'd at the meeting of Great Perſons. At his entrance into the Chamber he ſaluted thoſe Princeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and addreſſing himſelf to her who was the Object of his Vows, he ſaid to her, <q>Am I not unhappy, Madam, to have deſired a hundred times to be in the Prin. <hi>Alphonſus</hi>'s company at your Lodgings, and to have miſs'd this day ſo narrowly the opportunity of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying my deſire. You will recover it to morrow, reply'd ſhe with the ſame Familiarity, if you will meet here. Your Brother has promis'd to Regale us with the Recital of ſome Verſes, and ſome other Gallantry.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:54982:49"/>
            <p>As this young <hi>Prince</hi> was very Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent above all things on the ſubject of Love, the two hours which he ſpent in theſe Ladies company, he talked only of <hi>ſympathy</hi> of motions of <hi>Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> of the means to pleaſe, and of the ſweetneſs of a lovely <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> He with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew very late, ſo that our intimate <hi>Princeſſes</hi> had very little time to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain themſelves upon the ſubject of this Lover. Things not being ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced, but they could diſcourſe of him any other day at their leiſure, <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phigenia</hi> embraced her Companion, and remounted her Coach.</p>
            <p>She return'd next day to the <hi>Frin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes,</hi> where ſhe was preceded by <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus,</hi> and follow'd a little time after by the two <hi>Neopolitans.</hi> The Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs <hi>Iphigenia</hi> opened the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in praying the younger of the two Brothers to keep his word, and to let them ſee the Epitaph which he had promis'd them on a jealous man. He defended himſelf ſometime by a
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:54982:50"/>ſort of affected modeſty, from expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Verſes, of which they would with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt ſuſpect him to be the Author, and drew them at laſt out of his Poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, after having ſaid, <hi>That thoſe that were infected with this Diſtemper, were doubly unhappy; becauſe inſtead of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving compaſſion, the were do the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the Laughing-ſtock of the whole World.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="epitaph">
                        <head>The Epitaph of a Jealous Man.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Here in this Tomb a Jealous perſon lies,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who of all Sots and Blockheads was the Prince;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His Heart his Miſtriſs purchas'd with her Eyes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His Happineſs his Rivals have ſhar'd ſince.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb n="95" facs="tcp:54982:50"/>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Paſſengers, don't his Deſtiny bewail;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>A Jealous man deſerves no pity ſure:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>His fears were groundleſs, yet could nought prevail</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>O're his ſuſpitions, till Death wrought his Cure.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe Verſes ſeem'd, not to the Company ill turn'd, every one prais'd them; and <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who knew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the Subject of them, gave them his approbation. <hi>Iphigenia</hi> pray'd the Author of the Epitaph, to give her all the ſence which it contain'd; which he did more pedantickly than a Regent of a Colledge would have done. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> remembring the Order he had receiv'd the day before, was impatient that <hi>Iphigenia</hi> would ſet a foot the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject upon which ſhe was deſirous to hear this Parrat diſcourſe. That ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> had no trouble to bring this diſcourſe to the point ſhe deſired. She fell upon the Subject of Violent Paſſions, which gave <hi>Alphoniſus</hi> occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:54982:51"/>on to ask the Company for Examples of ſome Perſons who had been violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in love. Whereupon the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina</hi> taking the word, ſaid, <q>That Hiſtory could furniſh him but with too many Amorous Men for Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Women, and ſo on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. But that it ſeem'd as if Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage were the Deſtroyer of Love, and 'twas to railly a Wife, but to ſay that ſhe loved her Husband, and that ſhe could hardly believe there were Women to be found who had preſerv'd an ardent Love for their Husbands.</q> The young <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> who was on fire to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play his Knowledge, added, <q>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity can furniſh us with a very great number, and the laſt Ages are not unprovided. Without doubt, my Lord can produce ſome Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſaid <hi>Alphonſus.</hi>
               </q> Yes, my Lord, reply'd that young man, who had an itch to ſpeak, <q>I will, for the ſatisfaction of the Company, relate
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:54982:51"/>upon that Subject thoſe which my Memory ſhall furniſh me with. <hi>Artemiſa</hi> ſwallowed the Aſhes of her Husband. <hi>Hypſicratea</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King her Husband to the Army, and fought till Death by his ſide. Not to dwell upon what <hi>Virgil</hi> has written of <hi>Dido</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dromache; Panthaea</hi> the Wife of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bradates,</hi> kill'd her ſelf upon the dead Body of her Husband. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> the Wife of <hi>Demetrius,</hi> that King having loſt his Life in a Battle, poyſoned her ſelf. And not to go ſo high, does not our Age afford us a Wife who paſſionately lov'd her Husband, in that <hi>Iſabella,</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Salem,</hi> who not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to obtain leave to follow him to the Army, writ to him, that there paſſed not a Night but ſhe embraced him, and taſted the ſweeteſt Pleaſure with him: That ſhe made Vows for the changing
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54982:52"/>the Days which ſhe employ'd in weeping, into Nights, that ſhe might always enjoy his ſweet Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces. I perceive that this laſt Wife lov'd a little for Intereſt;</q> (interrupted the eldeſt Prince, who made a ſign to his Brother to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, judging thoſe kinds of Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>Pedantick</hi>) <q>and I believe that all Wives who have amiable Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, reſemble her.</q> The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian held his peace, and 'twas then that <hi>Alphonſus</hi> burſt out a laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which put him out of counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. This young Prince taking his laughing for an Affront which he did him, ask'd him if he believ'd not the truth of thoſe Hiſtories? whereupon he anſwered him, That he had likewiſe read them all in a Book of Fables, except the laſt, which ſhew'd more the Character of a voluptuous Wife, than of one tranſported by a virtuous Paſſion.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54982:52"/>This younger Brother ſaid nothing elſe, but that Truth would always paſs for a Lye, from a Rivals mouth. <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> who underſtood well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough what he drove at, pray'd him to explain himſelf. But the prudent <hi>Princeſſes</hi> fearing that the Diſpute growing hot, it might have dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſequences, roſe up; which made them thereupon break off, and gave them notice it was time to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Princeſſes</hi> being left alone, <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phigenia</hi> addreſſing her ſelf to her dear Companion, ſaid to her, <q>My God! Madam, how ſelf-conceited is this young <hi>Neopolitan?</hi> How full of himſelf? Is his Brother's Wit as ill turn'd? He is more moderate, reply'd ſhe, but his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is ſomewhat duller, it is not lively; and how well made ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be outwardly, he has not the Secret to pleaſe me. But now
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:54982:53"/>you put me in mind on't, What is the unknown Lover whom you now and then diſcourſe to me of? If you will conceal his Name, draw me his Picture at leaſt; for I doubt not but you have ſeen him. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, Madam, reply'd <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phigenia,</hi> and I will ſatisfie your curioſity thereupon. Know then, in the firſt place, that he is born a Prince, and that he hath been ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently favour'd by Fortune. He is young, and has never felt true Love for any but your ſelf. He loves you, he adores you, he ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies your Humour, he knows what Temper you are of, and he knows you as well as himſelf. He has Wit enough, which is ſparkling, lively, gay, and loves not trifles. He is generous and liberal: He has already given proof of his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in a ſingle Duel. He has a great Soul, and is as much an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:54982:53"/>to Cowardize as Quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. As to his Perſon, although he hardly is of a middle ſize, he is well ſet, and has a good Carriage: He is a little long Viſag'd, his Noſe a little turn'd up; he has black Eyes, large and even with his Head; and above all, paſſionate. His Mouth is little, his Eye-brows and Hair of a bright Cheſnut, and of an admirable gloſs. This is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what near his Picture; to which I ought to adde, to turn it to the light, that he has very much Love and Tenderneſs; that you are the onely Object of his Vows; that he ſighs continually at the fight of your Charms, and that the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of your Divine Qualities, make him ſo fearful, that he has not dar'd to declare his Paſſion to you. You draw me a Picture ſo charming in the Graces, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh this unknown Lover, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:54982:54"/>the Princeſs, that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but give the Lye to Poets, who maintain that an unknown Object cannot excite Motions of Love. I love this Prince; and ſince we may ſpeak freely together, the favour I have to ask of you, is, to inſpire him with Courage, that I may have the ſatisfaction to ſee him ſpeedily. I will endeavour, reply'd <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> to raiſe him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove that reſpectful Fearfulneſs which retains him; and I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that to morrow he ſhall have the honour to entertain you in Perſon, or by Letter. You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, added the Princeſs, oblige me more, than to procure me one of his Letters, if you cannot make him reſolve to come to ſee me. I ſhall judge by his Writing, if that Prince has Sentiments as tender as you have told me. To morrow then, Madam, you ſhall hear of
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:54982:54"/>him,</q> ſaid the Dutcheſs, retiring her ſelf.</p>
            <p>The Picture of ſo accompliſh'd a Lover, made ſuch an impreſſion on the <hi>Princeſs</hi>'s Spirit, that ſhe was employ'd with it all Night, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the eldeſt of our <hi>Neopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> who fail'd not a day of giving her marks of his Love, preſenting himſelf in the Morning at her <hi>Toi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let,</hi> found her thoughtful, and very cold. This young <hi>Prince</hi> having never obſerv'd in her any inequality of Humour, was extreamly ſurpriz'd to meet with ſo much indifference: But as a Lover always flatters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he thought that the <hi>Princeſs</hi> would try his Love; which made him tell her, That in her melancholy Fit, and her gay Humour, ſhe was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually amiable.</p>
            <p>The firſt Coldneſs put not this Prince in trouble. He examin'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon what he might have done,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54982:55"/>which was diſpleaſing to that Fair Ones Eyes, and thinking himſelf guilty of nothing, he believ'd that the day following might change her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who was engag'd to bring a Letter to the <hi>Princeſs,</hi> writ one, which ſhe caus'd to be tranſcrib'd by a young Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who div'd not at all into the Commerce of her Pleaſures, and who judg'd only that the Dutcheſs had a mind to divert her ſelf. The Letter contain'd what follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:54982:55"/>
                  <head>The Unknown Lover To the Princeſs, The moſt worthy to be belov'd.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MY Name and my Perſon, Divine Princeſs, are ſufficiently known to you. You are not ignorant of the diſpoſition of a Prince's heart, who would eſteem himſelf infinitely happy, if he could make you underſtand to what extreamity your Charms have reduc'd him. But how ſhould he draw you a Paſſion of the Character of his? I acknowledge that as accompliſh'd as you are, you are neither diſdainful, nor inſenſible, and that I may freely diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my Love to you. But who ſhall aſſure me of Life? one Refuſal, or the defect even of the return of your Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, being capable to give me
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:54982:56"/>Death. I have a hundred Reaſons to prohibit me your Houſe. Some Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces adore you; and I am the Subject of the Purſuits of a tender Love. I can only ſigh then, Madam, till Heaven diſpoſes of my Deſtiny, and inſpires you to be altogether favourable to the most faithful and paſſionate of your Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia</hi> found the <hi>Princeſs</hi> in the expectation of the Letter, whereby ſhe ſhould underſtand the Sentiments of her unknown Lover. Having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd it, ſhe read it with an incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible ſatisfaction. It had ſuch an Effect upon her Spirit, that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo impatient, and ſo curious to ſee him who was the Author of it, that nothing could entertain her ſo agreeably, as the repetition of the Promiſes which <hi>Iphigenia</hi> made her of making him reſolve to come to kiſs her hands. She believ'd ſhe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54982:56"/>ought not to anſwer this Letter. She imagin'd that the <hi>Dutcheſs,</hi> who would not divert her from her Love, was but too capable to aſſure that unknown Prince, of the eſteem that ſhe her ſelf had made her conceive for him. Wherefore ſhe contented her ſelf to pray her to animate his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, to flatter him with ſome hopes, and to perſwade him to become as bold as paſſionate.</p>
            <p>The young <hi>Neopolitan,</hi> impatient to try if the <hi>Princeſs</hi> were on his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count what ſhe had been the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, came to ask if he might have the honour to viſit her. But ſhe was ſo employ'd in thinking on the <hi>Billet</hi> which ſhe had receiv'd; that ſhe ſent him word ſhe was indiſpos'd. Although this Anſwer was an ill O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to him, he nevertheleſs did not diſpair of his Deſtiny, ſince he ſaw not any Perſon haunt her Houſe, whom he might fear to be his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54982:57"/>He return'd the next day to the Charge, and had the freedom to entertain the <hi>Princeſs</hi> in diſcourſe; whoſe Anſwers, for the moſt part, ſhew'd abſence of mind. He ventur'd to tell her, That he believ'd there was ſome Accident befallen her, which carried away her Thoughts. But he could not draw any thing from her; onely that ſhe was taken up with conſidering with her ſelf whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther having made choice of an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſhe could be capable to love al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways.</p>
            <p>This was an <hi>Enigma</hi> to our young Lover, I whom ſhe intreated to leave her ſome days at liberty. He went away overwhelm'd with the moſt cruel Melancholy that can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd, and was going to abandon himſelf, to his deſpair, when he met an old <hi>Chaplain</hi> of his Nation, to whom he diſcovered all the Secrets of his Soul. He pray'd him to aſſiſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54982:57"/>him with his Councel, and ask'd him if he knew what he might do to pleaſe. This old Fox, who had almoſt the direction of all the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of the Court, had experience enough to be able to give him ſome advice. He asked him firſt, if he had ſufficiently ſtudied the Humour of her whom he lov'd, to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered if his manner of Apparel, and his Trimming pleas'd her; and above all things, if his Garniture were of the colour which ſhe lov'd, or was ſuch that it might diſcover to her his Diſpoſition. And he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering, That he had follow'd in that onely the Mode, and Chance; the other reply'd to him, That thoſe ſort of things, when we have fine Qualities beſides, have a great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſhake the reſolution of a Maid; whom the leaſt Trifle may ſurprize. To inſtruct himſelf in the virtue of different Colours, this <hi>Prince</hi> led
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:54982:58"/>the <hi>Chaplain</hi> into the Kings Garden, where, in four or five turns of an Alley, he learnt from him the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Symbols.</hi> See here how that old man explain'd them to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>White,</hi> which is the moſt ſimple of all Colours, bears the character of <hi>Purity, Innocence,</hi> and <hi>Sincerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Black</hi> ſhews <hi>Perſeverance,</hi> becauſe it cannot be defac'd by any other Colour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Red</hi> denotes <hi>Revenge.</hi> It frights a Rival.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brown,</hi> and all dark Colours, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent <hi>Patience,</hi> and a ſerious Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carnation</hi> repreſents, extreamly well, the Grief which we feel for a loſt thing, which we hope to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aurora</hi> Colour is a ſign of <hi>Joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:54982:58"/>
            <p>The clear <hi>Violet</hi> Colour, the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delin,</hi> and the <hi>Peacock</hi> Colour, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to inſpire Love; they call it the Livery of <hi>Venus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Azure</hi> is a Token of Fidelity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it correſponds to Heaven, which appears always the ſame, when it is not obſcur'd by Clouds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grey</hi> or <hi>Aſh</hi> Colour, expreſſes Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy or Sadneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Green</hi> has always repreſented Hope, as the <hi>Fillemot</hi> Deſpair.</p>
            <p>Our ſad Lover minded not the old man had finiſh'd. He interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him here, and ask'd how he figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Indifference</hi> and <hi>Deſpight.</hi> 
               <q>By a mixture of all Colours, reply'd he. Good, reply'd the Prince. But at laſt, before I make uſe of this laſt Symbol, which of theſe Colours will ſuit me beſt, the <hi>Carnation,</hi> the <hi>clear Violet,</hi> the <hi>Blue,</hi> or in fine, which of all the others? It is not
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:54982:59"/>very eaſie for me, reply'd the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, to ſatisfie you poſitively there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon. The choice which you ought to make, depends very much upon circumſtances, which you muſt have examined before. A Lover ought not only to conſult himſelf and his Paſſion, but he ought to know perfectly the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of her whom he would pleaſe. <hi>White,</hi> as that which is mingled with it, ſympathices with the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of <hi>Phlegmatick</hi> Perſons. The melancholy Ladies love <hi>Black,</hi> and all which tends towards that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. <hi>Red,</hi> and all that comes near that Colour, is ſeen with pleaſure, by thoſe in whom Choler predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates: And <hi>Sanguine</hi> Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xions regard willingly <hi>Blue, Carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>Gredelin Aurora</hi> Colours, and all that are clear and ſhine. What! muſt one make all theſe obſervations, added the Prince? As
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:54982:59"/>far as I ſee, one muſt be a good <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher,</hi> to pleaſe. Without queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, reply'd the Old man, one muſt be very perfect in Phyſick, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe inſtead of gaining the glory of having pleas'd, one is expos'd to the diſcontent of being turn'd into <hi>Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule.</hi> But, Sir, reply'd he, if the Princeſs for whom you ſigh, hath a good Wit, as I queſtion not, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that if ſhe hath look'd on you favourably heretofore, and that ſhe is grown cold, without your having given her cauſe, you have a Rival. And 'tis what may put you to ſome trouble to diſcover. If you are not too ſcrupulous, I can ſhew you a Perſon, who without doubt can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you. Is he a Sorcerer, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the Prince? He paſſes for ſuch a one, continued the Old man; but I, who believe it not, I look upon him as a man who through the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that he has in Natural Cauſes, can with the help of certain Sands,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:54982:60"/>who have receiv'd the illuſtration of certain Stars, in a certain ſituation, and under a certain Aſpect, to ſmooth certain pieces of Earth with melted Flint-ſtones, which by virtue of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain blaſts, can render Objects at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance preſent; and above all, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent all ſorts of Letters, which have not been torn. So many <hi>Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> ſaid the Prince, laughing, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe me a very <hi>uncertain</hi> knowledge. Nevertheleſs, pray ſhew me the Lodgings of this great Philoſopher.</q> The Old man having inform'd him where he dwelt, he went thither all alone the ſame Evening, where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd the ſatisfaction which I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to relate. This <hi>Magician</hi> having led him, without Light, into a Cave, and having forthwith asked him if he were afraid, and the Prince having an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with aſſurance, that he was not, he drew a Circle with Cole, in the middle of which he plac'd him. Having after that, drawn out a certain
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:54982:60"/>dark piece of Earth out of a hole which he enlighten'd with certain Aſhes; and after ſome intelligible words, which frighted the <hi>Prince</hi> a little, who wou'd have been very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling not to have been there, he made appear to him, through that tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Body, the Letter which the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> his Miſtriſs had receiv'd; which he read from end to end. And this was all the knowledge which he could receive from the <hi>Magician,</hi> whom he ſatisfied according to his deſire.</p>
            <p>He had learnt but too much for his Repoſe; his Troubles increas'd. The Idaea of an unknown Rival, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his deſpair. He return'd to ſee the Princeſs, and found her ſtill the ſame; he gained all her Servants: he turn'd Spy himſelf; he poſted Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinels all round the Houſe, and could not diſcover him who diſputed his Love with him; ſometimes he is hot, and ſometimes fearful. He becomes a Prey to a deadly Melancholy, and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:54982:61"/>has recourſe again to <hi>Magick.</hi> He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts a Charm, and gives his conſent and all things neceſſary to the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of a <hi>Pomatum,</hi> which he deſigns to convey by ſtealth upon the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes <hi>Toilet,</hi> from whence he took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way for this purpoſe a little Pot which he caus'd to be fill'd with the following Ingredients, <hi>viz.</hi> the Scra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of Skins, the Cuttings of Hoofs, and Hairs imperceptibly cut off, burnt, and calcin'd with ſome drops of a certain Liquor, the whole at laſt mingled and incorporated with Sope, and common ſweet Powders; which Pot he cunningly ſubſtituted in the place of the other, and whoſe vertue had no Effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alphonſus</hi> on his ſide agreeably per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> who upon the great change of her outward Diſpoſitions, chang'd alſo her Inclinations, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd him with fair hopes, whilſt ſhe endeavour'd to inſpire the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs</hi> with Love for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nknown.</hi> She
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:54982:61"/>made her from day to day more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite deſcriptions of that <hi>Princeſs</hi>'s Paſſion, of which ſhe expreſs'd her ſelf to be ſenſible, when at laſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by her Prayers, ſhe engag'd to bring him to her on the morrow in the Evening. The <hi>Princeſs</hi> impatient to ſee the <hi>Cavalier,</hi> conjur'd her by the Union that was between them, to procure her the ſatisfaction of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and promis'd her, provided he was ſuch as ſhe had deſcrib'd him, to hearken favourably to his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as <hi>Iphigenia</hi> was return'd home, whether ſhe had carried <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia,</hi> ſhe ſent her to ſeek for the beſt Taylor of the Court, whom ſhe made to take meaſure of her, and to whom ſhe gave private orders to make her a magnificent Habit, with its Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, by Eight a Clock the next Night exactly, and to bring her choice of all things neceſſary to equip a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier for a Ball. The Taylor ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:54982:62"/>himſelf with an admirable diligence of his Commiſſion. The <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> ſent all the Equipage to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelia,</hi> whom ſhe had prepar'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and went to dreſs her ſelf in her Chamber, from whence ſhe ſent to demand if a ſtrange <hi>Prince</hi> might be admitted to make his Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to <hi>Madam.</hi> The Princeſs, who expected, according to <hi>Iphigenia</hi>'s promiſes, an unknown Lover, ſent to meet this <hi>Prince;</hi> ſhe was much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd to ſee him enter alone, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> would have bore him company. She advanced ſome ſteps to receive him, made a Seat be given him, and ordered her Attendants to withdraw, to enjoy all alone the pleaſures of this new Lovers Converſation, who began thus: <q>You ſee, Madam, the Perſon that the Dutcheſs <hi>Iphigenia</hi> has diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours'd of to you, according to what ſhe has told me; ſhe has made you a deſcription of me which ſcarce
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:54982:62"/>reſembles me. 'Tis the Effect of a bountiful Inclination, to which I ſhall be oblig'd all my Life. As e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent as ſhe has been upon the ſubject of my Paſſion, ſhe has ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs not amplified it, it is ſuch that I my ſelf who feel it, cannot deſcribe it to you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>She had not finiſh'd ſpeaking, when the Princeſs, who knew her again under her diſguiſe, reply'd to her thus: <q>I have always well preſum'd, Sir, that you were a Railleur who ſought to divert your ſelf. But I ſhould have been troubled to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelf that you had been deſirous to puſh your Raillery ſo far. It is no matter; I find you lovely, and I am very ready to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond your Paſſion. Give me your hand, Princeſs, ſaid the Dutcheſs then, and promiſe me that you will keep your word. The ſeaſon of the Carnival, which invites us to Joy, leaves us but juſt time enough
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:54982:63"/>to execute the Thing. I intreat your company to morrow at the Comedy which I will cauſe to be preſented before all the Court, and my Lord your Father. I will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſuch as I am, and in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion we will finiſh the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of our Marriage.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Princeſs,</hi> who imagin'd no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing loſs than what hapned, believ'd always that the Propoſitions which <hi>Iphigenia</hi> had made her, on the ſcore of an unknown Lover, were not feign'd; that ſhe would one day de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare what he was, and that in the mean while the time of <hi>Shrovetide</hi> would permit extraordinary Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. This made her give her Hand; purſuant to which, <hi>Iphigenia</hi> went to give order for all that was neceſſary for the celebration of their Nuptials on the morrow. She went to the <hi>King</hi>'s Apartment, the <hi>Queen</hi>'s, and all the <hi>Princes</hi> Lodgings, to pray them to honour that ſolemn Feaſt;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:54982:63"/>who expreſſed themſelves to be well ſatisfied with the divertiſements which the <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> would procure them All the Court were at the Comedy, and afterward went to the Dutcheſs's Houſe, where there was a ſplendid Supper provided.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iphigenia</hi> traveſty'd <hi>en Cavileer,</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> receiv'd there, with the conſent of them Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, all the Complements of the Court. The Articles of Contract were exhibited after the Regale<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> All the Court, after the King's Example, and the Princeſs's <hi>Father</hi> himſelf ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd it. The reſt of the common Formalities were obſerv'd. Our Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers mutually plighted their Faith to each other, and the Action was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, at which the eldeſt of the <hi>Neo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans</hi> and <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> ſhew'd all their good Humour.</p>
            <p>The Dutcheſs <hi>Iphigenia</hi> and the <hi>Princeſs</hi> her Spouſe, bore the quality of <hi>King,</hi> and the other <hi>Queen</hi> at the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:54982:64"/>Ball which followed. During the three hours which it continued, a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Poet met them, preſented them with an <hi>Epithalamium,</hi> whoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition was approv'd of. It was propos'd to conduct our new-married People to Bed. The <hi>King</hi> accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd them to the Chamber which had been prepar'd for them, at the door of which, it was believ'd that the laſt Scene would have a concluſion. They were notwithſtanding undreſs'd, and the Princeſs tyr'd as much with Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, as with the other Exerciſes of the Day, put her ſelf to Bed with <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phigenia,</hi> who inſtructed her with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration in what ſhe was ignorant of till then. The Curtains have robb'd me of the reſt. What? What we may believe as a Truth is, that the Bride was very much ſurpriz'd to find that Nature, liberal to <hi>Iphigenia,</hi> had indow'd her with both Sexes; that our Illuſtrious <hi>Hermaphrodite</hi> had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd from the bounty of a laudable
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:54982:64"/>Stock, what the weakneſs of a tender Age had ſcarce made her ſenſible of; that the Court imform'd of the Fact, at the ſollicitation of the Bridegroom's Father, who was very ſure of things, took all that had been done for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial and authentick; and that in fine, by the Alliance of this <hi>Gallant Hermaphrodite, Alphonſus</hi> had his Siſter for his Rival.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
